<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Sikhism Knowledge</string>

    <string name="navigation_drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>

    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>

    <!--Sik History Start-->

    <string name="golden_temple_string">Sri Harmandir Sahib or Golden Temple, (on account of its scenic beauty and golden coating for English speaking world), is named after Hari(God) the temple of God. The Sikhs all over the world, daily wish to pay visit to Sri Amritsar and to pay obeisance at Sri Harmandir Sahib in their Ardas.
    \n\n"SIKHAN NOO SIKHI DAN, KES DAN, REHAT DAN, BIBEK DAN, BHAROSA DAN, DANAN SIR DAN NAAM DAN, SRI AMRITSAR JI DE DARSHAN ISHNAN"
    \n\nIt is our request, Waheguru Ji, that Sikhs should have your grace to keep ‘Sikhi’, the hair(Kes), all the ‘Rehats’ (the commandments given by Guru Gobind Singh Ji), high intelligence, trustworthiness, and above all the supreme gift of remembering Your Name; they may be given the pleasure of visiting Amritsar.
    \n\n{ (Meaning Of Above Ardaas(Sikh Prayer) lines }
    \n\nGuru Arjan Sahib, the Fifth Nanak, conceived the idea of creating a central place of worship for the Sikhs and he himself designed the architecture of Sri Harmandir Sahib. Earlier the planning to excavate the holy tank (Amritsar or Amrit Sarovar ) was chalked out by Guru Amardas Sahib, the Third Nanak, but it was executed by Guru Ramdas Sahib under the supervision of Baba Budha ji. The land for the site was acquired by the earlier Guru Sahibs on payment or free of cost from the Zamindars (landlords) of native villages. The plan to establish a town settlement was also made. Therefore, the construction work on the Sarovar(the tank) and the town started simultaneously in 1570. The work on both projects completed in 1577 A.D.
    \n\nGuru Arjan Sahib got its foundation laid by a muslim saint Hazrat Mian Mir ji of Lahore on 1st of Magh, 1644 Bikrmi Samvat(December,1588). The construction work was directly supervised by Guru Arjan Sahib himself and he was assisted by the prominent Sikh personalities like Baba Budha ji, Bhai Gurdas ji, Bhai Sahlo ji and many other devoted Sikhs.
    \n\nUnlike erecting the structure on the higher level(a tradition in Hindu Temple architecture), Guru Arjan Sahib got it built on the lower level and unlike Hindu Temples having only one gate for the entrance and exit, Guru Sahib got it open from four sides. Thus he created a symbol of new faith, Sikhism. Guru Sahib made it accessible to every person without any distinction of Caste, creed, sex and religion.
    \n\nThe building work completed in 1601 A.D. on Bhadoon Sudi 1st, 1661 Bikrmi Samvat (August/September,1604). Guru Arjan Sahib installed newly created Guru Granth Sahib, in Sri Harmandir Sahib and appointed Baba Budha ji as its first Granthi i.e. the reader of Guru Granth Sahib. After this event it attained the status of ‘Ath Sath Tirath’. Now the Sikh Nation had their own Tirath, a pilgrimage center.
    \n\nSri Harmandir Sahib, is built on a 67ft. square platform in the centre of the Sarovar(tank). The temple itself is 40.5ft. square. It has a door each on the East, West, North and South. The Darshani Deori (an arch) stands at the shore end of the causeway. The door frame of the arch is about 10ft in height and 8ft 6inches in breath. The door panes are decorated with artistic style. It opens on to the causeway or bridge that leads to the main building of Sri Harmandir Sahib. It is 202 feet in length and 21 feet in width.

    \n\nThe bridge is connected with the 13 feet wide ‘Pardakshna’ (circumambulatory path). It runs round the main shrine and it leads to the ‘Har ki Paure’ (steps of God). On the first floor of ‘Har ki Paure’, there is continuous reading of Guru Granth Sahib.

   \n \nThe main structure of Sri Harmandir Sahib, functionally as well as technically is a three-storied one. The front, which faces the bridge, is decorated with repeated cusped arches and the roof of the first floor is at the height of the 26 feet and 9 inches.
   \n \nAt the top of the first floor 4 feet high parapet rises on all the sides which has also four ‘Mamtees’ on the four corners and exactly on the top of the central hall of the main sanctuary rises the third story. It is a small square room and have three gates. A regular recitation of Guru Granth Sahib is also held there.

    \n\nOn the top of this room stands the low fluted ‘Gumbaz’(dome) having lotus petal motif in relief at the base inverted lotus at the top which supports the ‘Kalash’ having a beautiful ‘Chhatri’ at the end.

    \n\nIts architecture represents a unique harmony between the Muslims and the Hindus way of construction work and this is considered the best architectural specimens of the world. It is often quoted that this architecture has created an independent Sikh school of architecture in the history of art in India.

    \n\nContinue Reading about Golden Temple’s Art and Architecture , Jalau ,Maryada and contribution of Maharaja Ranjit Singh</string>
    <string name="Martyrdom">Timeline of Martyrdom Week when Wadde Sahibzaade Sahibzada Ajit Singh ji,Sahibzada Jujhaar Singh Ji, and Chhotte Sahibzaade
        Sahibzada Zorawar Singh Ji and Sahibzada Fateh Singh ji got shaheedi at Chamkaur
        Sahib and Fatehgarh Sahib respectively.
\n\n* ਸ਼ਹੀਦੀ ਹਫਤਾ *
\n\n20 ਦਸੰਬਰ ਤੋਂ 27 ਦਸੰਬਰ ਤੱਕ

\n\n6 ਪੋਹ /20 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਸਵੇਰੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਨੇ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਸਮੇਤ ਅਨੰਦਪੁਰ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਦਾ ਕਿਲਾ ਛੱਡਿਆ ।

\n\n6 ਪੋਹ /20 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਦੀ ਰਾਤ ਗੁਰੂ ਜੀ ਅਤੇ ਵਡੇ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦੇ ਕੋਟਲਾ ਨਿਹੰਗ ਰੋਪੜ ਵਿਖੇ ਨਿਹੰਗ ਖਾਂ ਕੋਲ ਰਹੇ

\n\nਛੋਟੇ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦੇ ਅਤੇ ਮਾਤਾ ਗੁਜਰੀ ਜੀ ਕੁੰਮੇ ਮਾਸ਼ਕੀ ਦੀ ਝੁਗੀ ਵਿਚ ਰਹੇ

\n\n7 ਪੋਹ/21 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਗੁਰੂ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਅਤੇ ਵਡੇ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦੇ ਸ਼ਾਮ ਤੱਕ ਚਮਕੌਰ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਪਹੁੰਚੇ

\n\nਛੋਟੇ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦੇ ਅਤੇ ਮਾਤਾ ਗੁਜਰੀ ਜੀ ਨੂੰ ਗੰਗੂ ਬ੍ਰਾਹਮਣ ਆਪਣੇ ਪਿੰਡ ਖੇੜੀ ਲੈ ਗਿਆ

\n\n8 ਪੋਹ/ 22 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਚਮਕੋਰ ਗੜੀ ਦੀ ਜੰਗ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋਈ ਬਾਬਾ ਅਜੀਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਜੀ ਉਮਰ 17 ਸਾਲ ਭਾਈ ਮੋਹਕਮ ਸਿੰਘ (ਪੰਜਾ ਪਿਆਰਿਆਂ ਵਿਚੋਂ ) ਅਤੇ 7 ਹੋਰ ਸਿੰਘਾ ਨਾਲ ਸ਼ਹੀਦ ਹੋਏ

\n\nਬਾਬਾ ਜੁਝਾਰ ਸਿੰਘ ਉਮਰ 14 ਸਾਲ ਭਾਈ ਹਿੰਮਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਅਤੇ ਭਾਈ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਸਿੰਘ (ਪੰਜਾ ਪਿਆਰਿਆਂ ਵਾਲੇ ) ਅਤੇ ਤਿੰਨ ਹੋਰ ਸਿੰਘਾਂ ਸਮੇਤ ਸ਼ਹੀਦ ਹੋਏ ਅਤੇ

\n\n8 ਪੋਹ / 22 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਨੂੰ ਹੀ ਮੋਰਿੰਡੇ ਦੇ ਚੋਧਰੀ ਗਨੀ ਖਾਨ ਅਤੇ ਮਨੀ ਖਾਨ ਮਾਤਾ ਗੁਜਰ ਕੌਰ ਜੀ ਅਤੇ ਛੋਟੇ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਗੰਗੂ ਦੇ ਘਰੋਂ ਗ੍ਰਿਫਤਾਰ ਕਰਕੇ ਤੁਰ ਪਏ

\n\n9 ਪੋਹ / 23 ਦਿਸੰਬਰ : ਨੂੰ ਰਾਤ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਤੜਕ ਸਾਰ ਗੁਰੂ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਸਿੰਘਾ ਦੇ ਹੁਕਮ ਅੰਦਰ ਚਮਕੋਰ ਦੀ ਗੜੀ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਨਿਕਲ ਗਏ

\n\n9 ਪੋਹ /23 ਦਿਸੰਬਰ : ਦੀ ਰਾਤ ਦਸ਼ਮੇਸ਼ ਜੀ ਨੇ ਮਾਛੀਵਾੜੇ ਦੇ ਜੰਗਲ ਵਿੱਚ ਅਤੇ ਦਾਦੀ ਸਮੇਤ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦਿਆਂ ਨੇ ਸਰਹਿੰਦ ਦੇ ਠੰਡੇ ਬੁਰਜ ਵਿਚ ਗੁਜਾਰੀ

\n\n10 ਅਤੇ 11 ਪੋਹ/ 24 ਅਤੇ 25 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਦੋ ਦਿਨ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਰਹਿੰਦ ਦੇ ਸੂਬੇ ਨਵਾਬ ਵਜ਼ੀਰ ਖਾਨ ਦੀ ਕਚਹਿਰੀ ਵਿਚ ਪੇਸ਼ ਕੀਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਅਤੇ

\n\nਪਿਤਾ ਦਸ਼ਮੇਸ਼ ਜੀ ਉੱਚ ਦੇ ਪੀਰ ਬਣ ਪਿੰਡ ਆਲਮਗੀਰ ਤੱਕ ਸਫਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਰਹੇ

\n\n12 ਪੋਹ / 26 ਦਸੰਬਰ: ਬਾਬਾ ਜ਼ੋਰਾਵਰ ਸਿੰਘ ਉਮਰ 7 ਸਾਲ ਅਤੇ ਬਾਬਾ ਫਤਿਹ ਸਿੰਘ ਉਮਰ 5 ਸਾਲ ਸੀ ਦੋਵੇਂ ਨੀਹਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਚਿਣ ਕੇ ਸ਼ਹੀਦ ਕੀਤੇ ਗਏ।

\n\nਮਾਤਾ ਗੁਜਰ ਕੌਰ ਜੀ ਠੰਢੇ ਬੁਰਜ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਵਾਸ ਤਿਆਗ ਗਏ।

\n\n13 ਪੋਹ ./ 27 ਦਸੰਬਰ ਨੂੰ ਤਿੰਨਾ ਦਾ ਦੇਹ ਸਸਕਾਰ ਸਤਿਕਾਰ ਯੋਗ ਮੋਤੀ ਰਾਮ ਮਹਿਰਾ ਅਤੇ ਟੋਡਰ ਮੱਲ ਨੇ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਕੀਤਾ ।</string>

    <string name="whether">Qazi and maulvis got together and began discussing religion.
A great fantasy has been created and no one could understood its mystery.
They asked Baba Nanak to open and search in his book whether Hindu is great or the Muslim.
Baba replied to the pilgrim hajis, that, without good deeds both will have to weep and wail.
Only by being a Hindu or a Muslim one can not get accepted in the court of the Lord.
As the colour of safflower is impermanent and is washed away in water, likewise the colours of religiosity are also temporary.
(Followers of both the religions) In their expositions, denounce Ram and Rahim. The whole of the world is following the ways of Satan
– Taken from a Shabad by Bhai Gurdaas Ji in Vaars Bhai Gurdaas</string>


    <string name="guru"> After Guru Ramdas had taken the gurgaddi he still continued doing lot of physical sewa. Once Baba Sri chand , son of Guru Nanak ji decided to meet Guru Ramdas ji. As soon as the word traveled to Ramdas ji, Guru Ramdas sent his followers to meet Sri Chand ji at the edge of the city and himself left his sewa to meet him. When Baba Sri Chand saw guru Ramdas he was shocked because with his yogic eyes he saw his father Guru Nanak in Guru Ramdas ji. He proclamed you are the image of my father .. you have the light of my father, but your beard is much longer than my father! why is your beard so long ?? Guru Ramdas ji answered – my beard is so long so that I can wipe the feet of the saints like u and he actually bent over to rub over Sri Chand’s feet. This surprised Sri Chand ji who jumped back and said even after so many years of ‘tap’ I have’nt been able to achieve this grace and humility. I have never seen such humility beofre. you are the king. you sit on the throne. you are the king of the yoga. They both enjoyed the meeting after that.
    ” With the rising of the sun, the Gurmukh speaks of the Lord. All through the night, he dwells upon the Sermon of the Lord. My God has infused this longing within me; I seek my Lord God. ||/||
    My mind is the dust of the feet of the Holy. The Guru has implanted the Sweet Name of the Lord, Har, Har, within me. I dust the Guru’s Feet with my hair. ||/||Pause|| – GGS ji pg:1355
    Soon the word spread that Sri Chand ji declared Ramdas ji as the yoga king.. the yogi’s stated to question what yoga does he knows and what is the throne he sits on ???.. so when they came to Guru Ramdas ji, ramdas ji told them to chant gods name instead of ausetrities and stop violence against their body, and instead of going to caves and leaving everything, live in your “grisht ashram” (homes) and bring moderation to your eating, sleeping and to your sensuality ..don’t deny yourself as a human but bring moderation to it and infuse yourself with moral courage ( sahaj yoga) and by these things they will gain union with god.. the way of yoga the celebs have adopted had actually seperated them from god for when they came close/in presence of a woman their equilibrum was disturbed bcos they were still humans.. Guru Ramdas told them to keep their equilibrium day and night by meditation and chanting gods name. and focusing on gods feet.
    You may pluck the strings with your hand, O Yogi, but your playing of the harp is in vain.
    Under Guru’s Instruction, chant the Glorious Praises of the Lord, O Yogi, and this mind of yours shall be
    imbued with the Lord’s Love. ||/||
    O Yogi, give your intellect the Teachings of the Lord.
    The Lord, the One Lord, is pervading throughout all the ages; I humbly bow down to Him. ||/||Pause|| You sing in so many Ragas and harmonies, and you talk so much, but this mind of yours is only playing a game
    You work the well and irrigate the fields, but the oxen have already left to graze in the jungle. ||2||
    In the field of the body, plant the Lord’s Name, and the Lord will sprout there, like a lush green field. O mortal, hook up your unstable mind like an ox, and irrigate your fields with the Lord’s Name, through the Guru’s Teachings. P||
    The Yogis, the wandering Jangams, and all the world is Yours, O Lord. According to the wisdom which You give them, so do they follow their ways.
    O Lord God of servant Nanak, O Inner-knower, Searcher of hearts, please link my mind to You. ||¥||9||6/||
    – GGS ji pg:368
    He further explained.. yoga is acceptance of both polarities ..good and bad .. when there is no good no bad .. ( kaun bhale ko mande) ?? when u accept all of it as god then you merge with god in ecstacy. and this is true yoga
    </string>

    <string name="Golden">The path from Town Hall to Golden Temple will be a heritage walk for all visitors. From Baba Saheb Ambedkar Statue to Maharaja Ranjit Singh, From Martyred Singhs to Festival Timings, the walk will take you in different eras before you reach the Golden Temple Complex</string>
    <string name="A">There’s a story about a saint who lived in his own anand, he cared about everyone and everyone loved him. Another blessed man also lived in the same town. One day a childless woman went to see the blessed man, she said , ‘Ask your God to grant me a son’. The Blessed man went to the top of the mountain and spoke to God of the poor woman’s request. He came back and told the lady, ‘God said that there are no children in your destiny’.

A few days later, the woman came back full of joy and happiness, she was giving sweets to one and all, the blessed man asked what she was celebrating. She replied, ‘The Saint has said I will be blessed with a beautiful baby boy, my dreams have come true!’.

The blessed man couldn’t understand it, he climbed the mountain and asked God ‘O Lord You said the lady had no children in her destiny, yet the saint has granted her a son. How can he overrule your decision?’ God replied, ‘O Blessed Man, before I answer that, go to the town and tell my children’s (villagers) that God wants a pound of their flesh.’

The Blessed Man spent the next few days telling everyone, they looked at him and ran away, no-one was prepared to give a pound of flesh. Then the Saint met him and he told him of the strange request to which the saint replied, ‘O Blessed Man, go back to God and ask him from which part of my body he wants it from.’

On top of the mountain the blessed man said to God, ‘Only the saint was prepared to obey your command, Lord. Even I was scared to obey it.’ God then answered him, ‘My Saint is prepared to die for me, I am bound by what he says. My saint can overturn destiny, everything belongs to the saint.’</string>
    <string name="bibi">“When the Mughal forces laid siege around Anandpur Sahib, many Singhs deserted the Guru, including the 40 Singhs who later became the 40 Muktas. Guru Gobind Singh Jee asked Bibi Basant Kaur if she wanted to leave the fort, as there would be terrible hardships in the coming months. However Bibi Jee politely declined, saying that she would not leave her Guru whatever the circumstances.

After some months of real difficulties and hunger, Guru Gobind Singh Jee decided to leave Anandpur Sahib at the request of his Sikhs. Evading the Mughal forces, the Guru and his Sikhs reached the River Sirsa. It was the winter months, and due to the cold weather and fast flowing river current, the Sikhs got scattered. Guru Gobind Singh Jee, Sahibzada Ajit Singh and Sahibzada Jujhar Singh got separated from Mata Gujjer Kaur ( Mata Gujri), Sahibzada Zorawar Singh and Sahibzada Fateh Singh.

Bibi Basant Kaur was with Mata Gujjer Kaur at this critical time, leading Mata Jee’s horse through the River Sarsa. Mata Jee’s horse led her to the other side of the river, but Bibi Basant Kaur got swept away by the cold but rapidly flowing river water. As the river carried her for some distance, she fell unconscious due to the horrendously cold water. Finally her body was washed up on the side of the riverbank.

A Mughal soldier, Samund Khan, seeing Bibi Basant Kaur unconscious, took advantage of her vulnerability and took her to his house. When she regained her consciousness, he asked her to accept Islam and become his wife. He said if she accepted his wishes, she would have all the material pleasures that she could ever dream of. Bibi Jee replied: “I could have left my Guru months ago and not had to endure such hardships at Anandpur Sahib. I will never leave my Guru.” Samund Khan was taken aback by Bibi Jee’s response, but thought leaving her locked up and hungry in a cell for some days would easily break her resolve.

Bibi Basant Kaur’s health was already in a bad state, but throughout her stay in the cell, she resolved to make Gurbani her Aasra. She sat cross-legged in one spot, but with deep concentration and faith in Waheguroo, she kept doing Sukhmani Sahib da Paath. No fears about the future could remove her concentration from Guru Jee and Gurbani.

When Samund Khan came to Bibi Jee after eight days, her resolve was nowhere near broken. This left Samund Khan seething with anger. Evil thoughts crossed his mind. He started to move towards Bibi Jee. Bibi Jee realised the situation, and started praying to Kalgidhaar Dasmesh Pita.

Samund Khan was saying in an antagonising and sarcastic manner “what’s your Guru going to do for you now? Are you ready to accept Islam now?” Bibi Jee responded “My Guru is always with me. You cannot do anything to me.” “Don’t lie … your Guru is nowhere to be seen,” he said in a taunting manner, as he moved further towards Bibi Jee. Bibi Jee started to do Ardaas to Guru Sahib with even greater pyaar and faith. Suddenly, out of nowhere, Bibi Jee said “My Guru is here.” He was now within touching distance of Bibi Jee. He said, “I cannot see him … you’re imagining things.” Bibi Jee said, “you will not be able to see him … you’re a Paapi person, full of the 5 vices. Only those with high Kamayee can see him. My Guru Jee is here with me.”

“gur maerai sa(n)g sadh aa hai n aalae || simar simar this sadhaa samh aalae ||1|| rehaao ||”

My Guru is always with me, near at hand. Meditating, meditating in remembrance on Him, I cherish Him forever. ||7||Pause|| – Guru Granth Sahib Ji Pg 394

At this instance, Samund Khan tried to move further towards Bibi Jee, yet his body had now frozen. Although he could see with his eyes and speak with his mouth, all his body’s muscle had frozen, as if he was a statue. Bibi Jee had realised what her Guru Jee had done. She asked, “I thought you said my Guru would not save me? I thought you said he was not here?”

After a few minutes of being frozen like a statue, he started begging Bibi Jee to do Ardaas to unfreeze him. Bibi Jee said that her Ardaas would only happen if Samund Khan promised to be a decent God-fearing person. Samund Khan readily agreed. Bibi Jee did her Ardaas, and Guru Gobind Singh Jee unfroze the Mughal soldier. For the following few weeks, having seen the Kamayee and Gursikhi Jeevan of Bibi Basant Kaur, he served Bibi Jee very well whilst Bibi Jee continued doing Bhagti. He then took Bibi Jee personally to Dina Kangoor to re-unite Bibi Jee with Guru Gobind Singh Jee.

What can we learn from this episode?

Guru Jee is always with us, but only those fortunate souls with high Bhagti and Naam Jeevan realise this. Such souls can speak, feed, see and call upon their Guru all the time and at any time.

If we are to reach this stage, we must have full faith in the Guru, incorporate his teachings into our lives and never leave the Guru … just like Bibi Basant Kaur Jee.

If we become Bhagats of Waheguroo, Waheguroo will always preserve our honour, saving us physically whilst having mortal form and saving us forever once our soul leaves the body.</string>
    <string name="bhagat">“Jin Prem Kiyo Tin Hi Prabh Paayo” – Guru Gobind Singh ji => Pure Love Leads to God

Trilochan awoke early daily just to have sight of Namdev,

Together they would concentrate on the Lord and Namdev would tell him the grand stories of God.

(Trilochan asked Namdev) “kindly pray for me so that if the Lord accepts, I may also have a glimpse of His blessed vision.”

Namdev asked Thakur, the Lord, as to how Trilochan could have sight of the Lord ? The Lord God smiled and explained to Naamdev;

“No offerings are needed by me. Out of my delight only, I would make Trilochan to have sight of me. ”

i am under the total control of the devotees and their loving claims i can never reject; rather I myself also cannot understand them.

Their loving devotion, in fact, becomes mediator and makes them meet me.”

– Bhai Gurdaas Ji in Vaars Bhai Gurdaas on Pannaa 10</string>

    <string name="the">There is a Sakhi (historic event) about a great Sant Sipahee.(Saint-Soldier).. he truly had attained one-ness with Waheguru ji and had mastered weaponary too. In the battlefield he fought for justice. His opponent had been overpowered and lay on his back on the floor. The Sant-sipahee was about to destroy the sinner by plunging the sword of Akal into his chest, when the opponent spat in the Sant-Sipahee’s face.

The Sant-Sipahee’s blood boiled, rage and fury burned him for a moment, he raised his sword with new fervour.but stopped the sword in mid-swing!. The enemy was shocked, expecting to be dead, he grunted ‘Kill Me Sikh, you have beaten me’.

The Sant-Sipahee replied, ‘Before I was fighting for justice, against the evil actions of your army, and destroying you was destroying injustice . When you spat in my face I wanted to kill you because you insulted ME. I was going to kill you out of ANGER AND HATE which would have been wrong and against the principle of Sikhi/Khalsa. I would have to have been reborn because of that, so I have spared you’.

The enemy soldier was so incredibly amazed at the Khalsa soldier, that within a few months he left his troops and joined the Khalsa.

Criticise and Punish the Actions,

Love the Person…… It’s a hard path to follow …. finer than a hair and

sharper than a sword .

“Kabeera, janaa gyan tah Dharam hai jahaa jhooth tah paap” – (Guru Granth Sahib Ji) Kabeer, where there is spiritual wisdom, there is righteousness and Dharma. Where there is falsehood, there is sin.
    </string>

    <string name="faq">WHAT IS THE DEFINITION OF A SIKH?
\n\nThe most widely accepted definition of a Sikh comes from the Sikh code of conduct, the Rehat Maryada. Originally written in Punjabi, it is translated as:
“A Sikh is any woman or man whose faith consists of belief in:
One God,
The ten Gurus, from Guru Nanak to Guru Gobind Singh,
The Guru Granth Sahib,
The utterances and teachings of the ten Gurus,
Who has faith in and aspires to take Amrit, initiation ceremony into the Khalsa,
And who does not owe allegiance to any other religion.”
As with most religions, however, a devotee cannot be confined to a definition.

\n\nHOW MANY SIKHS LIVE IN THE UNITED STATES? WHEN DID SIKHS FIRST IMMIGRATE TO AMERICA?
\n\nThere are over 500,000 Sikh Americans, and Sikhs have been in America for over 100 years.

\n\nWHY DON’T PEOPLE KNOW ABOUT SIKHISM EVEN THOUGH IT IS THE 5TH LARGEST WORLD RELIGION?
\n\nThere are several different reasons. First, Sikhism, compared to other world traditions, is relatively young. The faith first emerged in 1469. Second, since many people are not aware that Sikhism is the fifth largest world religion, it is not referenced when discussing the other world religions. For example, many school textbooks have incorrect or no information on the faith.

\n\nIS THERE AN OFFICIAL SIKH GREETING?
\n\nThe tenth Sikh Guru instructed Sikhs to greet each other with “Waheguru ji ka Khalsa, Waheguru ji ki Fateh” (“The Khalsa belongs to Waheguru (the Divine) and victory belongs to Waheguru”). Another common Sikh greeting is “Sat Sri Akal” (“Truth reigns eternal”).

\n\nIS THERE A SIKH EMBLEM OR SYMBOL? WHAT IS THE HISTORICAL SIGNIFICANCE OF THE KHANDA?
\n\nThe Ik Onkar and the Khanda are some of the symbols of the Sikhs. According to the Sikh scholar Kapur Singh, the Khanda first appeared around the eighteenth century.
“The Khanda is the symbol of the Sikhs, as the Cross is to Christians or the Star of David is to Jews. It reflects some of the fundamental concepts of Sikhism. The symbol derives its name from the double-edged sword (also called a Khanda) which appears at the center of the logo. This double-edged sword is a metaphor of divine knowledge, its sharp edges cleaving truth from falsehood. The circle around the Khanda is the chakar. The chakar being a circle without a beginning or end symbolizes the perfection of God who is eternal. The chakar is surrounded by two curved swords called kirpans. These two swords symbolize the twin concepts of meeri and peeri – temporal and spiritual authority introduced by Guru Hargobind. They emphasize the equal emphasis that a Sikh must place on spiritual aspirations as well as obligations to society.” This information was obtained from http://www.sikhs.org/khanda.htm.

\n\nIS THERE A PARTICULAR ‘SIKH COLOR’? SAFFRON?
\n\nNo, there is no particular color for Sikhs or Sikhism. The Sikh flag, which is seen at almost every Gurdwara, is a bright orange/saffron color or dark blue. These represent traditional colors for Sikhs.

\n\nWHY DO SO MANY SIKHS HAVE A COMMON NAME, SINGH OR KAUR?
\n\nThe tenth Sikh Guru, Guru Gobind Singh, created the unique identity of the Sikhs and also gave all Sikh men one last name – Singh and all Sikh women another – Kaur. The reason for doing so is strongly rooted in the culture of South Asia. In that time period’s caste-ridden society and even today, someone’s last/family name signifies their social status and caste. Guru Gobind Singh wanted to remove these barriers between people, and create an egalitarian society. The word Singh means Lion and the word Kaur denotes Princess.

\n\nDO SOME SIKHS KEEP THEIR LAST (CASTE) NAME? WHY?
\n\nMany Sikh families have kept their family name, but have maintained Singh and Kaur as middle names.

\n\nDO SIKHS HAVE ANY DIETARY RESTRICTIONS? CAN SIKHS EAT MEAT?
\n\nSikh Gurus strongly forbade all rituals and superstitions. Sikhs are thus not allowed to eat any food prepared through a ritualistic process (e.g., Sikhs are not meant to eat Kosher or Halal). There is no mandate allowing or disallowing Sikhs to eat meat. Sikhs are also not supposed to drink alcohol or consume any other intoxicants.

\n\nIS THERE A SIKH CEREMONY OF INITIATION?
\n\nYes. Initiated Sikhs are said to have joined the “Khalsa.” Joining the Khalsa is an important step in one’s life. You are pledging your commitment to this faith and agreeing to live your life as a Sikh. This means that you must wear the five articles of faith, and carry Singh or Kaur as your last name.

\n\nHOW OLD DO YOU HAVE TO BE TO BE INITIATED?
\n\nThere is no prescribed age at which a Sikh should be initiated and can choose to do so whenever he or she is ready. According to the Rehat Maryada, only those who understand the significance of the ceremony and carry its discipline with sincerity should be initiated. It is important that once you are initiated you are committed to that lifestyle.

\n\nWHY DON’T SIKHS CUT OR SHAVE THEIR HAIR?
\n\nThe founders of the Sikh faith started the practice of keeping hair unshorn. Guru Gobind Singh, the tenth Sikh Guru, gave the Sikhs 5 articles of faith (including unshorn hair), which as a whole comprise the daily uniform of a Sikh. In other words, keeping your hair (kesh) and wearing a turban form an external identity for a Sikh.

\n\nHOW ABOUT PEOPLE WITH CUT HAIR WHO IDENTIFY THEMSELVES AS SIKH?
\n\nAll Sikhs are supposed to have uncut/untrimmed hair. But like in every religion, there are people who closely follow the religion and others who may not. Some people may cut their hair, but that does not exclude them from the Sikh community.

\n\nDO WOMEN SHAVE?
\n\nSikhs are not supposed to cut hair from any part of their body. All Sikhs are thus supposed to have unshorn hair, and Sikh women are to maintain a separate identity and not shave.

\n\nCAN I TOUCH SOMEONE’S TURBAN OR HAIR?
\n\nDo not touch someone’s turban or hair without asking, as it may make him/her uncomfortable.

\n\nWHAT IS UNDER YOUR TURBAN?
\n\nHair. Sikhs keep their hair unshorn and tie it in a bun or top knot on top of his/her head.

\n\nWHAT DOES THE COLOR OF THE TURBAN MEAN? DO ALL SIKHS WEAR THE SAME COLOR? WHY OR WHY NOT?
\n\nSikhs can wear any color or style of turban, and there are no significant colors. Some Sikhs wear very few colors and others have a broad color palette.

\n\nHOW CAN I TELL THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN SIKH TURBANS AND OTHER TURBANS?
\n\nEver Sikh ties his or her turban slightly differently. Remember that in America, 99% of the people you see wearing a turban will be Sikh. If you see someone wearing a turban and you are not sure if they are Sikh or not, ask them!
The Sikh turban is thus an article of faith. People of many other cultures and religions wear turbans, but none are required to do so by their religion.
Sikhs tie their turbans anew each day. Sikh turbans become a part of a Sikh’s body and are usually removed only in the privacy of the house.

\n\nDO WOMEN WEAR TURBANS?
\n\nJust like Sikh men, Sikh women are not supposed to cut their hair. In the Rehat Maryada, it is explicitly written that Sikh men wear a turban. There is nothing explicitly written about women, except that the turban is optional. Traditionally, women have always covered their head, but we’ve seen in the last 50 years, that women have deviated from this. There are many reasons for this change: globalization, cultural trends, and a lack of clarity in the Rehat Maryada. For Sikh women who tie a turban, the turban is just as much a part of their body and identity as it is for Sikh men!

\n\nWHY DO SIKHS WEAR A KIRPAN? WHAT SIZE KIRPAN DOES A SIKH CARRY?
\n\nA kirpan does not have a prescribed length. In most cases it is about 3-9 inches long. The kirpan serves as a reminder to fight against injustice and oppression. A Sikh understands that carrying a kirpan is a great responsibility. It is only intended to protect themselves or others.

\n\nDO KIDS IN SCHOOL CARRY A KIRPAN?
\n\nSome Sikhs that are younger have made the choice to become initiated, and as such, do wear a kirpan. Oftentimes, school personnel are aware that the Sikh student wears a kirpan, and both parties have come to an understanding as to how the student may wear his/her kirpan.

\n\nWHAT HAPPENS WHEN A SIKH GOES ON AN AIRPLANE? DO YOU HAVE TO TAKE THE KIRPAN OFF?
\n\nAt the present time, Sikhs put their kirpans into check-in luggage and do not carry it with them on an airplane.

\n\nCAN I VISIT A GURDWARA?
\nEveryone is welcome at a Gurdwara regardless of their race, religion, color or class. If you are interested in visiting a Gurdwara, feel free to reach out to Sikhs you know or contact community@sikhcoalition.org for additional suggestions and ideas.

\n\nDO YOU HAVE TO BE A SIKH TO READ THE GURU GRANTH SAHIB?
\n\nAnyone who wishes to can read the Guru Granth Sahib.

\n\nDO SIKHS HAVE A CLERGY? WHAT ABOUT GRANTHIS/GIANIS?
\n\nNo. Sikh gurus were very clear about each Sikh making her or his own journey and not depending on a clergy to show them the way. Sikhs do have Granthis/Gianis. These are people who have studied the Sikh scriptures extensively, and are available in the Gurdwaras as teachers. They often lead a congregation, but any members from the congregations – both men and women – can also perform the same ceremonies.

\n\nCAN WOMEN EXECUTE DUTIES IN A GURDWARA OR CONGREGATION?
\n\nYes. Sikhism does not delineate/define certain tasks to only men or only women. A woman can lead or take part in any service or ceremony just as a man would.

\n\nWHY ARE MEN AND WOMEN DIVIDED INTO SEPARATE SECTIONS WHILE SITTING IN THE GURDWARA?
\n\nSikh Gurus always taught equality between men and women. For instance, the Gurus decried the cultural climate that denied women access to religion and gave women equal rights as men in all spheres.
In Sikh congregations, men and women are asked to sit side by side – women on one side of the Guru Granth Sahib, and men on the other. There are both practical and cultural reasons for this practice. Since everyone sits on the floor, often unintentionally touching the person next to them when there is a large congregation, having such interaction with the member of the opposite gender is frequently inappropriate in the cultural context in which Sikhism arose.
However, in some smaller Gurdwaras, men and women may be seen sitting mixed in the congregation.

\n\nWHAT IS LANGAR?
\n\nThe Sikh Gurus instituted the unique practice of Langar. Langar is food that is cooked by the members of the community and served by members of the community, to all people at the Gurdwara. All Gurdwaras have a common kitchen, where Langar is cooked by volunteers and open to all. Langar is communal cooking, eating and sharing. Langar is eaten while sitting on the ground. The idea is to demonstrate equality of all people, irrespective of caste, creed, religion, race or sex. When Sikhism was sprouting in the South Asian subcontinent, the caste system stratified society. Higher castes would sit on stools and chairs and eat, while the lowest caste were not allowed to eat even in the same room, and usually on the floor, away from sight. The Gurus wanted Sikhs to always practice egalitarianism and communal responsibility. Langar represents one of the institutions the Gurus founded to break down caste barriers.

\n\nWHAT IS THE SIKH WEDDING CEREMONY?
\n\nThe Sikh marriage ceremony is called Anand Karaj. It is performed in the presence of the Guru Granth Sahib, the Sikh scripture. In a Sikh wedding, scripture is read from the Guru Granth Sahib, and after each section the couple walks around the Guru Granth Sahib, showing their commitment to the teachings being read. This is done four times. Following this, a communal prayer is said for the couple and religious hymns are sung. The ceremony may be performed by any initiated member of the Sikh faith. The prayers being read indicate that the couple pledge allegiance to each other as well as the Sikh way of life and make a commitment to working together to help each other realize the Divine Presence.

\n\nDO YOU BELIEVE IN AN AFTERLIFE? DO YOU BELIEVE IN HEAVEN/HELL, SALVATION?
\n\nSikh focus is on this lifetime. The Sikh Scripture ask Sikhs to make the best of their time on this earth, for this is one’s opportunity to accomplish her or his best and to make a connection with Waheguru – the One, Omnipotent Power. Sikhs are asked not to partake in rituals and superstitions and not to concentrate on what occurred before birth or after death. Sikh scripture repudiates a belief in a physical place called Heaven or Hell. Similarly, Sikhism rejects the notion of a Judgment Day. Sikhs believe in the doctrine of karma, which is a cosmic law that takes into account a person’s good and bad actions during his or her lifetime. The person then is rewarded or must endure suffering based on his deeds. The Sikh scripture supports the idea of reincarnation.

\n\nFUNERALS – WHERE, WHAT, HOW?
\n\nAccording to the Sikh Rehat, Sikhs may dispose the body of the dead in any way they like. Sikhs generally cremate their dead because it is clean, simple and environmentally friendly. The body is bathed and clothed in fresh clothes by family members, and community members say collective prayers. The ashes are usually gathered afterwards, and put afloat in a flowing body of water – returning the person’s last physical remains to nature.

\n\nWHAT DOES SIKHISM TEACH ABOUT OTHER RELIGIONS?
\n\nThe Sikh scripture, the Guru Granth Sahib, is the only major religious text which contains writings by teachers of other faiths. This is because Sikh gurus taught that there are many different ways of achieving a connection with the God. The Sikh way is one of these ways. If you are following the Sikh way, you must follow it to the best of your abilities, and with absolute devotion.

\n\nDOES SIKHISM TRY TO CONVERT OTHERS?
\n\nNo. Sikhism forbids proselytization or forced conversions. Sikhism believes that there are many paths to achieving attunement with the Divine. However, Sikhism welcomes those interested in learning about the religion. Thus, people might learn about Sikh faith and then even be initiated as Sikhs. There are Chinese Sikhs, African Sikhs etc. However, once someone is initiated as a Sikh, she or he must follow the Sikh path to the best of her or his ability.
    </string>

    <!--Sik History End-->



    <string name="gurus"> <![CDATA[  <h3>Guru Nanak Dev Ji</h3>

Guru Nanak was born in 1469 at Rai Bhoeki Talwandi now known as Nankana Sahib situated in Punjab province of West Pakistan . This place is about 55 miles north-west of Lahore . His father, Mehta Kalu was a Patwari- an accountant of land revenue in the government. Guru’s mother was Mata Tripta and he had one older sister, Bibi Nanki. From the very childhood, Bibi Nanki saw in him the Light of God but she did not reveal this secret to anyone. She is known as the first disciple of Guru Nanak.

<br><br>GURU’S SCHOOLING:

<br><br>At the age of seven, Guru Nanak was sent to school, which was run by teacher, Pandit Gopal Das, at his village. As usual the teacher started the lesson with an alphabet but the teacher was wonder-stuck when the Guru asked him to explain the meanings of the letters of the alphabet. However at the helplessness of his teacher, the Guru wrote the meanings of each and every letter of the alphabet. This was the first Divine Message delivered by Guru Nanak. This was an explanation of deeper truth about human beings and God and the way to realize God in terms of the alphabet. The teacher stood abashed before the Divine Master and bowed to him. He then took him back to his father and said, “Mehtaji, your son is an Avtar (prophet) and has come to redeem the victims of Kalyug (the age of Falsehood). He is destined to be a world Teacher, there is nothing that I can teach him.”

Many writers believe that Guru Nanak was first sent to different schools belonging to the Hindus and Muslims to learn about Vedas (Hindu Scriptures) and Quran (Muslim Scripture), and only after obtaining the knowledge from those scriptures, he started his religion. According to Malcolm, Guru Nanak is said to have learnt all earthly scenes from Khizr -the Prophet Elias. “There is a reason to believe,” writes Cunningham, “that in his youth he made himself familiar with the popular creeds both of Mohammadans and the Hindus and that he gained a general knowledge of the Quran and Brahmanical Shastras.”

It seems that all these scholars of history have not grasped the basic fundamental fact about the divinity of Guru Nanak. He was born with divine status, thus, his teachings were heavenly. These writers seem to be very much ignorant of the fact that Guru Nanak was an Embodiment of Divine Light.He was a celestial being and his divine attributes put him above mankind and its schools. Historians have failed to visualize the splendor in Guru’s Jot. Heavenly Spirit does not learn from man-made institutions. He was a heavenly messenger and a born world teacher who taught the mankind the path of righteousness and truth. Guru Nanak’s divinity is above all earthly institutions and their teachings. The Message that Guru Nanak gave to this world, came to him direct from God as he confirms himself: It is also mentioned in the Janamsakhi (biography) that many times Guru Nanak said to his companion Mardana, “Mardana, play the rebec, the Divine Word is coming.” This confirms the fact that education from the Hindu and Muslim religious institutions, had no bearing at all on the Divine Word that Guru Nanak received from God and delivered to this world. To say that Guru went to different institutions to learn, is violating the sanctity of Guruship.

<br><br>CEREMONY OF SACRED THREAD:

<br><br>Guru Nanak was nine years old and according to the custom among the higher castes of Hindus, he was required to invest himself with the sacred thread called ‘Janaeu’. Great preparations were made by his father for this ceremony. The family priest named Hardyal, started chanting Mantras (Hindu hymns) and was ready to put the thread around Guru’s neck when he refused to wear it. The whole assembly was astonished. They tried to persuade him every way to wear the Janaeu but in vain.

<br><br>COBRA SERVES THE DIVINE MASTER:

<br><br>As usually is the case in villages, the father sent his son to graze the buffaloes in the pastures. One day while the Guru was grazing the buffaloes, he fell asleep under a tree and the herd destroyed the crops in the neighboring fields. When the owner saw his crops damaged, he became furious and lodged a complaint with Rai Bular, an officer-in-charge of that area. Rai Bular sent for the son and his father to adjust the quarrel. The Guru told them that no damage was done to the crops; rather it was blessed by God. Rai Bular sent his messengers to inspect the fields. But to everybody’s surprise the investigators could not find any damage in the fields rather the crops were doubly blossoming. The field where this miracle happened is now known as Kiara Sahib. On another day the Guru was sent to graze the buffaloes in the pastures and he fell asleep under the shade of a tree. As the sun rose higher, the shadow moved away. A big cobra came out of its den and provided shadow with its hood over the face of the Divine Master. Rai Bular happened to pass by that side with his attendants. When he saw this strange scene, he was convinced that the boy was a man of God. Upon seeing the people, the cobra retreated to its den and Rai Bular touched Guru’s feet in great reverence and thus became Guru’s disciple.




        <h3>SRI GURU ANGAD DEV JI</h3>

Guru Angad Dev was born on March 31, 1504 in a village called Harike in Ferozepur district of the Punjab . His father, Bhai Pheru was a trader. His parents called him Lehna. He was married at the age of fifteen. His wife, Khivi was a native of Mattei di Sarai in Ferozepur district. His father grew weary of Harike and with his family returned to his ancestral place, Mattei di Sarai and lived there. Bhai Lehna’s wife gave birth to two daughters, Amro and Anokhi, and two sons called Dasu and Datu.

When Mattei di Sarai was sacked by the Mughals and Baloches, Bhai Lehna and his father moved to Khadur, now a famous town near Tarn Taran. Bhai Lehna grew very religious under the influence of his mother, Daya Kaur, and became a devotee of Durga, the goddess of Shakti. He used to organize yearly pilgrimage of devout Hindus to Jawalamukhi, a place of Durga temple in the lower Himalayas where fire issued from the mountains. He used to lead Durga dance around the fire in a harness of jingling bells.

Bhai Jodha, a Guru’s Sikh, lived in Khadur and it was his daily routine to rise early every morning and recite Japji and Asa di Var. One day as Bhai Lehna attentively listened the Divine Sabad recited by Bhai Jodha, his mind obtained peace. After the day break he asked Jodha who had composed that stimulating hymn. Bhai Jodha then told him all about Guru Nanak, who was living at Kartarpur at that time. The touch of Divine Sabad made such an impact on Bhai Lehna’s mind that he got impatient to meet the Guru. When he was on his annual pilgrimage to Jawalamukhi, he broke his journey at Kartarpur to offer his obeisance to the Guru. During his meeting, the Guru spoke to him of the True Creator, leaving such an impression on Bhai Lehna that he threw away the jingling bells, which he was carrying with him to dance before the goddess. He had obtained such a peace of mind that he decided to discontinue his pilgrimage and abide with the Guru. On seeing his increasing devotion, the Guru said to him one day that he should go home and settle his affairs and on his return he would initiate him as his Sikh. Upon this Bhai Lehna returned to Khadur for some time.

One day as Sikhs assembled, Guru Nanak seated Bhai Lehna on his throne, put five paise and a coco-nut in front of him and bowed before him and then said to Bhai Buddha,”This is my successor- Guru Angad; put a tilak on his forehead in token of his appointment to the Guruship.” Bhai Buddha did so. The Guru then ordered his followers to obey and serve Guru Angad; who was in his own image

After his appointment to the Guruship, Guru Nanak directed Guru Angad to return to Khadur. Upon this Guru Angad returned to Khadur and lived there.

<br><br>GURU ANGAD IN SECLUSION:

<br><br>The Guru sat in a room locked from outside near Khadur, and meditated on God without any distraction or interruption. He did not eat or drink anything except a pot of milk daily. About six months passed like this and the Sikhs did not know the whereabouts of the Guru. One day Bhai Lalo, Bhai Saido and Bhai Ajita and other Sikhs came to Bhai Buddha and asked him the whereabouts of the Guru. They had searched Khadur and other places but could not find him anywhere. It is said that Bhai Buddha concentrated his thoughts on the Guru and was able to visualize his place of meditation. Next morning they all went to the house near Khadur where the Guru was sitting in seclusion. The owner of the house gave them no information but went inside the house and told the Guru about the visit of four Sikhs. The Guru told the owner that they should be shown inside

<br><br>Bhai Buddha requested him to take his seat as Guru and receive the Sikhs publicly. After this Guru Angad came forth from his seclusion. When the Guru came out, crowds went to see him and presented to him their offerings. Whatever he received, the Guru passed on to his kitchen. There were continuous preaching, singing of hymns and repetition of Name.

<br><br>GURMUKHI SCRIPT:

<br><br>Clipped or imperfect alphabet of Punjabi existed at the time of Guru Nanak, but Guru Angad modified and polished the existing script. Since the Guru had adopted the modified alphabet, it was called ‘Gurmukhi’- spoken through the mouth of the Guru. The significance of the adoption of this script by Guru Angad lies in the fact that he rejected all other scripts, and adopted the script which was his own and suited to the language of the people. It also helped to enhance their culture. The Guru recorded everything onwards in Punjabi in Gurmukhi script.






        <h3>SRI GURU AMARDAS JI</h3>

Guru Amar Das was born on April 5, 1479 at Basarka village in Amritsar district. He was the eldest son of his parents, Bhai Tej Bhan and Mata Lakhmi. At the age of 24, he was married to Mansa Devi who gave birth to two sons, Mohan and Mohri, and two daughters, Bibi Dani and Bibi Bhani.

<br><br>DATU’S ANIMOSITY:

<br><br>Guru Angad’s sons were upset because they claimed that after their father, they were the legitimate heirs to Guruship. Guru Angad’s son Datu, therefore, proclaimed himself as Guru in Khadur; but the Sikhs did not accept him as such. Secondly under Guru Amar Das’s strict dictum, it was mandatory that all persons, high or low, rich or poor, king or the commoner, Brahmans or Sudras, and Hindus or Muslims, must sit in the same row as equals to dine in the Guru’s langar (kitchen). This had upset the Brahmans very much and they were on the search of an opportunity to rectify this situation. These Brahmans and other higher caste leaders saw some chance in Datu’s revolt to capture the Guruship. Upon their support, Datu proceeded to Goindwal where the Guru was stationing.

<br><br>Guru Amar Das was sitting on his religious throne and was delivering instructions to the congregation. Datu came along with a large number of his companions and kicked the Guru, who fell down the platform. Datu took possession of the platform and proclaimed himself as the Guru. Guru Amar Das got up and said in extreme humility,”Sir, pardon me, my hard bones might have hurt your tender feet.” After this the Guru left Goindwal and went to his village Basarka. He confined himself in a house outside the town without letting anybody know about his whereabouts.

Datu sat on Guru’s throne in Goindwal and was very proud of his position. The Sikhs, however, did not accept him as Guru, and all the pilgrims to Goindwal went away on hearing of the insult to their Guru. On seeing the Sikhs’ contempt towards him, one day Datu loaded his newly acquired wealth on a camel and returned to Khadur. On his way he was encountered with some robbers who seized the camel with the load, and one of the robbers struck Datu on the same foot with which he had kicked the Guru. Datu’s foot swelled up and caused him great pain.

The Sikhs were very much distressed at loosing their Guru. They searched all over but could not find him anywhere. Under the leadership of Bhai Buddha, they prayed and then let Guru’s mare loose and anxiously followed it for a short distance. The mare made her way to the Guru’s house in Basarka, and stood before his door. It was written on the door,”Whoever openeth this door is no Sikh of mine, nor I am his Guru.” They did not open the door, but made an opening in the wall and made supplication before the Guru. The Guru could not disregard the love and devotion of his Sikhs and returned to Goindwal. The Guru’s return was celebrated with illuminations, rejoicing and feasting.






     <h3>SRI GURU RAM DAAS JI</h3>

  Many writers have expressed their opinion that Akbar granted the land only to Guru Ram Das on which he founded the city of Ramdaspur (later known as Amritsar), and so they contend that the city of Amritsar was not founded during the time of Guru Amar Das. It is also a well-known fact of Sikh history that Emperor Akbar came to Goindwal and he dined with the common people in the Guru’s langar before he could see the Guru. It seems that the Emperor granted the estate in the name of Bibi Bhani at that time, and Jethaji being her husband, was made incharge of the estate by Guru Amar Das. Guru Nanak awarded the Guruship to Bhai Lehna and not to his sons, and it is quite obvious that in order to avoid hostility of his sons towards his successor, he asked Guru Angad to move to Khadur instead of continuing to live in Kartarpur. The same circumstances prevailed during the reign of second and third Gurus. It is, therefore, quite likely that the planning of a new city was called for during the reign of Guru Amar Das as mentioned in the previous chapter.

Guru Ram Das left Goindwal for his new colony. Many Sikhs followed the Guru and settled there. At first this city was called Ramdaspur, which is now called Amritsar.

A revenue collector of Patti in district of Lahore had five daughters, the fifth daughter was very religious. One day the father asked who gave them to eat and drink. The first four daughters said that it were their parents who had provided them with food and other necessities of life, but the fifth daughter told her parents that God was the only Cherisher of His creation. On hearing this reply her father got very angry and remarked,”I shall see if God will protect you.”

One day a crippled leper came to the town and the father married his fifth daughter to him to teach her a lesson. She willfully accepted him as her true husband. She put him in a basket and carried him on her head, and begged from door to door to maintain their livelihood. One day she left him under a tree near a pool of water and went to the nearby colony to beg for food. The leper saw some crows (black in color) dipping in the water and they turned white when came out of the water. The leper thought that the water had some miraculous healing property. So he left his basket and crawled into the water, and lo, the leprosy at once disappeared from the body except one finger which was left out of water. When the lady came back, she did not believe the story of the healed leper. Ultimately they went to Guru Ram Das, who confirmed saying that the pool possesseth such extraordinary efficacy which the man alleged. Upon this the couple became Guru’s followers and they worked in the excavation of the tank later on.

The tree under the shade of which she left her husband, is still standing there and is called ‘Dukhbhanjni Beri’. The pool was known as Amritsar- tank of nectar, the place itself came to be known as the city of Amritsar. The work was not finished by Guru Ram Das but it was completed by his successor, Guru Arjan Dev.



<h3>SRI GURU ARJAN DEV JI</h3>



Guru Arjan was born in Goindwal, a small town in Amritsar district, on April 15, 1563 . He was the youngest son of Guru Ram Das and Bibi Bhani. As a child, one day he found his way to the bed of Guru Amar Das who was then resting. His mother ran to fetch the child before he could disturb the Guru, but he had already awakened the Guru, who revealed, “Let him come to me; ‘yeh mera dohita bani ka bohita howega’- this grandson of mine shall be a ship to take mankind across the ocean of the world.”

Guru Arjan was married to Ganga , daughter of Krishen Chand, a resident of Meo village near Phillor in Jullundhur district. The marriage took place in 1589 when he was about 26 years old. Guru Ram Das began excavation of two tanks named Santokhsar and Amritsar and started the foundation of the city of Ramdaspur . After his father, Guru Arjan applied himself to the task of completing the tanks and extending the city. It was his practice to go every day and superintend the work.

<br><br>MASAND SYSTEM:

<br><br>Guru Nanak during his missionary tours had established Sangats at the various places throughout the country. The connection with the center was kept up by the constant visits of the Sikhs to the Guru. During Guru Amar Das’s time the missionary work became more regular and methodical. He divided the Sikh spiritual kingdom into twenty-two Manjis. Guru Ram Das established the nucleus of a new order of missionaries called Masands. The word Masand seems to have come from ‘Mas Nad’ which is shorter form of ‘Masnedi-Ali’ or His Excellency, the title which the Mughal Governors often held. The purpose of this organization was to spread the Sikh faith at a rapid pace and also to collect money for the construction of tanks and the city of Ramdaspur . Guru Arjan organized Masand system afresh. He appointed new Masands of integrity and sincerity to look after the secular as well as spiritual affairs of the Sikhs. Masands were required to collect Daswandh (one-tenth of income) from the Sikhs which was then contributed towards the Guru’s treasury (Golak) for the maintenance of the Sikh temples.

Some writers are of the opinion that Daswandh was raised under compulsion. Daswandh was never raised under any pressure nor it was considered ‘a tax’. Whatever the Sikhs contributed or are contributing even today, is totally out of free will, love and devotion.

Masands were required to pay annual visits to Amritsar at the Baisakhi fair to receive instructions from the Guru and to hand over the amount of Daswandh collected. Regular accounts of these offerings were kept and receipts were issued.

Apart from financial duties, Masands were vigorous preachers. For the ceremony of initiation the ideal Charanamrit was the one administered by the Guru himself. Since it was not possible for the Guru to be present physically everywhere, the authority was delegated to the local missionaries to enrol new members of the Sikh Sangat by administering Charanamrit prepared by themselves in the prescribed manner. It attracted a large number of converts. During the time of Guru Arjan, there was hardly any place in India where the Sikhs were not found. Masands worked very hard to propagate Sikhism in every corner of the country.



<h3>Sri Guru Hargobind Sahib Ji</h3>



Guru Har Gobind was born to Guru Arjan on June 19, 1595 at Wadali, a village near Amritsar. The period of Guru’s early life is alluded to in the previous chapter. After the Martyrdom of his father (Guru Arjan), the Guru caused the Adi Granth to be read by Baba Buddha and the musicians of the temple sang the Gurus’ hymns. This lasted for ten days. When the final rites were over, Baba Buddha started the ceremony of Guruship. It should be remembered here that when Guru Arjan’s wife went to Baba Buddha for boon of a son, she had prepared the meals with her own hands, and she took bread with onions. Baba Buddha while eating had said, “The Guru is the owner of the storehouse, but I have received an order to open it. As you have given me food to my heart’s content, so shall you have a son to your heart’s content. He shall be very handsome and brave, possess spiritual and temporal power, become a mighty hunter, ride on royal steeds, wear two swords, be puissant in battle, and trample on the Mughals. As I crush these onions you have brought to me, so shall your son crush the heads of his enemies, and be at once a great warrior and exalted Guru.” As usual Baba Buddha placed before the Guru a seli (a woolen cord worn as a necklace or twisted round the head by the former Gurus) and a turban, as appurtenances of his calling. The Guru ordered the seli to be placed in the treasury and reminding him about his prophecy said to Baba Buddha, “My endeavors shall be to fulfil thy prophecy. My seli shall be a swordbelt, and I shall wear my turban with a royal aigrette. Give me a sword to wear instead of seli.” The sword was brought. The Guru said, “Bring another one, I shall wear two swords.” He wore two swords which were emblems of Spiritual and Temporal authority- Piri and Miri- the combination of ‘Bhagti and Shakti’.

<br><br>AKAL TAKHT:

<br><br>The martyrdom of Guru Arjan was an unparallel act in the history of mankind. The Guru went through all that torture to show to the world how in all thick and thin one should cheerfully submit to the sweet Will of God. As a matter of fact, the contents of the Adi Granth were not meant for the Yogis, Sidhas and Sanyasis or the Muslim Suffis only, who sit in seclusion in the caves of the Himalayas and worship the Almighty by denouncing the world. Instead the teachings of the Adi Granth were meant for the family men. Leading the family life, the Gurus gave practical examples as how to live according to Guru’s Word. The cruel and tortuous execution of Guru Arjan aroused a very strong wave of angry feelings among the masses. The enlightened, but not passive, sufferings of the Guru instilled a new spirit and life into the people and they resolved to exert and sacrifice themselves for the sake of righteousness. For centuries, countless people had fallen under the aggressor’s sword and this did not soften the stone hearts of their oppressors; but rather they had become more cruel and brutal. Sometimes it might be possible to reform the evil doer by opposing untruth and injustice through non-violent methods. The silent resistance and suffering for righteous cause might sometimes enable the tyrant to see his evil actions and he might be improved. History stands witness that no amount of non- violence can succeed against a tyrant who is hardened and steeped in criminal oppressive ways and who pays no heed to basic values of moral and civilized conduct. Against such men, non-violence is only another name of disgraceful cowardice in their dictionary. Such power drunk men must be faced bravely with a stick bigger than theirs. After the inauguration, some Masands represented to the Guru’s mother that the preceding five Gurus never handled arms; if Emperor Jahangir heard about this, he would be angry and where would they (Sikhs) hide? She spoke the young Guru on the subject.

The Guru issued an order to the Masands that he would be pleased with those who brought offerings of arms and horses instead of money. He laid down the foundation of Akal Takht (Timeless Throne) in 1606 (the fifth day of light half of month of Harh, Sambat 1663) just in front of Harmandar, and it was completed in 1609. Akal Takht was built of solid bricks on a raised platform of about ten feet in height and looked like a throne. The Guru took his seat on it. He built Akal Takht a few yards in front of Harmandar with a view that a Sikh at Akal Takht should not forget that spiritual elevation was as essential as his social obligations. As a matter of fact, the Guru wanted his followers to be ‘saint-soldiers’, extremely cultured, highly moral with spiritual height and be ever-ready to measure swords with demonic forces. “In the Guru’s house religion and worldly enjoyment shall be combined- the caldron to supply the poor and the needy, and the scimitar to smite the oppressors.” (This should be noted by those Sikhs who say that worldly and practical affairs should be kept separate from religion in our Gurdwaras). Several warriors and wrestlers came to the Guru for service. He enrolled fifty-two heroes as his body-guard and this formed the nucleus of his future army. About five hundred young persons came from all over the Punjab to enlist in his service. He made Bhai Bidhi Chand, Bhai Jetha, Bhai Piara, Bhai Langaha, and Bhai Pirana, each captain of a troop of one hundred horse. People began to wonder how the Guru could continue to maintain such an army. The Guru quoted:
“God provideth every one with his daily food; why, O man, art thou immersed planning;
He putteth their food even before the insects which He created in rocks and stones.”
<br><br>(Gujri Mohalla 5, p-495)


<h3>Sri Guru Har Rai Ji</h3>



Guru Har Gobind had five sons and one daughter. The eldest son was Baba Gurditta who had two sons, Dhir Mal and Har Rai. Dhir Mal turned out disloyal and disobedient. He had some influence in the court of Emperor Aurangzeb and was in communication with the Guru’s enemies. When Guru Har Gobind moved to Kiratpur, Dhir Mal with his mother, remained at Kartarpur and took possession of the Guru’s property and also of the priceless original copy of the Adi Granth. He thought that as long as he had its possession, the Sikhs would look upon him as their religious leader and thus as mentioned in the last chapter, Dhir Mal refused Guru’s invitation to come to Kiratpur on his father’s death. Guru Har Gobind nominated Har Rai, younger brother of Dhir Mal, as his successor before he departed for the heavenly abode on March 3, 1644 .

One day as a child, while passing through a garden, his loose flowing robes damaged some flowers and scattered their petals on the ground. This sight effected his tender heart and brought tears in his eyes. After that he always walked with his skirts tucked up, and resolved never to harm anything in the world. When he grew up, he carried the same spirit with him. He used Baba Farid’s quotation frequently:

“All men’s hearts are jewels; to distress them is not at all good;

If thou desire the Beloved, distress no one’s heart.”

Guru Har Rai was most magnanimous. His food was very simple, he did not desire dainty dishes. Whatever valuable offerings were made to him, he used to spend on his guests. On the advice of his grandfather, Guru Har Gobind, he kept twenty-two hundred mounted soldiers. In the afternoon he used to go to chase. The Guru took some of the animals he had obtained from the chase, freed them and protected them in a zoological garden, which he had made for the recreation of his followers. In the evening the Guru used to hold his court, listen to hymns sung by his choir, and then give divine instructions.

The Emperor Shah Jahan had four sons, Dara Shikoh, Shuja Mohammad, Aurangzeb, and Murad Bakhsh. Dara Shikoh who was the heir-apparent, was very dear to his father. Aurangzeb was very clever, cunning and ambitious, and aimed at succeeding to the throne. It is said that Aurangzeb administered tiger’s whiskers in a dainty dish to Dara Shikoh who became dangerously ill as a consequence. The best physicians were consulted but in vain. The Emperor, filled with anxiety, sent for astrologers and diviners from every country but of no avail. The wise men arrived at a conclusion that until tiger’s whiskers were removed from Dara’s bowls, there was no hope of recovery. They were of the opinion that if a chebulic myrobalan weighing fourteen chitanks (14/16th of a pound) and a clove weighing one masha could be administered to the patient, he would be restored to health. The Emperor searched for these articles everywhere in his empire but in vain. At last some one told him that the required items were available in the Guru’s storehouse. On the advice of his courtiers the Emperor found it necessary to humble himself before the Guru, and accordingly addressed him the following letter:

“Your predecessor, the holy Baba Nanak granted sovereignty to Emperor Babar, the founder of my dynasty; Guru Angad was exceedingly well disposed to his son, Emperor Humayun; and Guru Amar Das removed many difficulties from my grandfather Akbar’s path. I regret that the same friendly relations did not subsist between Guru Har Gobind and myself, and that misunderstandings were caused by the interference of strangers. For this I was not to blame. My son Dara Shikoh is now very ill. His remedy is in your hands. If you give the myrobalan and the clove which are available in your store, and add to them your prayers, you will confer an abiding favor on me.”

A noble carried the letter to the Guru at Kiratpur, who commented, “Behold, with one hand man breaks flowers, and with the other he offers them, but flowers perfume both hands alike. Although the axe cuts the sandal-tree, yet the sandal perfumes the axe. The Guru is, therefore, to return good for evil.” He sent the necessary medicine which was administered to Dara Shikoh. The medicine effected a speedy and complete cure. The Emperor was naturally very pleased, forgot all enmity against the Guru, and vowed that he would never again cause any annoyance to him.

One day during a ride, the Guru halted and knocked at the door of a poor woman and said, “Good lady, I am very hungry, bring me the bread you have prepared.” The woman, throbbing with joy, brought out some coarse bread which he partook on horseback, without washing his hands, and relished it very much. He then blessed the woman and cut off the shackles of her transmigration. Next day the Sikhs prepared dainty dishes with great attention to cleanliness and offered them to the Guru at the same hour. He laughed and said, “O Sikhs, I ate food from that woman’s hands because she was holy. This food which you have prepared with attention to ancient ceremonial is not pleasing to me.” The Sikhs asked, “O true king, yesterday you ate bread on horseback from the hands of an old woman whom you did not know. There was no consecrated space and the food was in every way impure. Today we have prepared the food for you; no impurity is attached to it, yet you reject it. Be kind enough to explain the reason.” The Guru replied, ” The woman with great devotion and faith prepared food for me out of what she had earned from the sweat of her brow. On this account the food was very pure, and I partook of it. The Guru is hungry for love and not for dainty dishes. In the matter of love for God, no rule is recognized. It is not what man eats that pleases God, it is man’s devotion that is acceptable to Him.”




<h3>Sri Guru Harkrishan Ji</h3>



Guru Har Krishan who was the second and the youngest son of Guru Har Rai and Mata Krishen Kaur, was born on 7th of July, 1656 at Kiratpur. The reason why Ram Rai was superseded has already been given in the last chapter. Guru Har Krishan was appointed Guru when he was five years and three months old.

Ram Rai was at the Emperor’s court in Delhi and when the news of Guru Har Krishan succession to Guruship reached Ram Rai, he was inflamed with jealousy. The masand Gurdas who attended on Ram Rai comforted him,” There is no need to be sad. Thou hast many disciples in this part of the country. Even the Emperor himself holdeth thee in honor.” Ram Rai was not satisfied,” Knowest thou not, when the Sikhs of this country learn that the Guruship hath been given to my younger brother, they will turn away from me and go to him.” However Ram Rai acted on Gurdas’s suggestion and sent his masands in every direction to proclaim his succession and bring him the offerings of the faithful. His masands went in all directions to announce his succession as Guru but the Sikhs who knew Guru’s succession, refused to accept Ram Rai as their Guru. At that time Ram Rai decided to lay his case before the Emperor. Thus he addressed Aurangzeb,”Sir, my father has appointed my younger brother as successor to him, and now he has taken possession of his throne, his property and offerings. This misfortune has befallen me on account of my obedience to your Majesty. My father was opposed to you on that account, and at his death he ordered my younger brother never to be reconciled to you, and never to look upon your face. Now I pray thee to summon him to Delhi and order him to exhibit miracles as I have done.”

This situation provided the Emperor with a good opportunity to realize his own religious mission. Aurangzeb wanted to convert all Hindus to Islam but he apprehended failure in Punjab because the people greatly revered the Guru there. If the Emperor could get Ram Rai the Guruship, and through him he would perhaps be able to spread Islamic faith in Punjab , or even if he were successful to set both brothers at variance, they would die by mutual slaughter, his purpose should be served.

Aurangzeb having contrived this wicked plan, called Raja Jai Singh of Amber (Jaipur) and ordered him to summon Guru Har Kishen and said,” I wish to see him, be careful that he (Guru) be treated with all respect on his journey.” Ram Rai was delighted to hear the Emperor’s decision to summon his brother.






<h3>Sri Guru Teg Bahadur Ji</h3>



‘Baba Bakale’, was the only clue given by Guru Har Kishen for his successor. As this word reached the village Bakala, twenty-two Sodhis including Baba Dhir Mal, the grandson of Guru Har Gobind, set up their shops and claimed themselves as the ninth Guru. The Sikhs were in great confusion as they could not know who the real Guru was. Makhan Shah Labana of Jehlem district was a trade merchant. When his vessel full of merchandise was sinking, he had invoked Guru Nanak and had vowed to offer five hundred gold mohars (coins) if the vessel reached the shore safely (some say that he vowed 101 gold mohars). Makhan Shah came to the village of Bakala to pay his offering to the Guru. He was surprised to find that twenty-two Sodhis had installed themselves as Gurus. In that state of confusion and uncertainty, he resolved to try the pretenders. He thought to put two mohars before each impostor and the real Guru being the searcher of hearts, would ask for the balance of his promised offering. He visited all the 22 impostors and made each of them offering of two gold mohars, but none of them asked for the balance.

He then inquired if there was any one else in Bakala. Someone informed him about Guru Tegh Bahadur. Makhan Shah went and as usual made his offering of two gold mohars. Upon this Guru Tegh Bahadur asked,” How now, O Sikh, thou art trying to wheedle the Guru by presenting him with only two gold mohars? Where are the balance of five hundred gold mohars you had promised when your ship was sinking?” Mukhan Shah was delighted and prostrated himself before the Guru. He then went to the roof of the house and screamed,” Guru Ladho! Guru Ladho!” ‘I have found the Guru! I have found the Guru!’

Guru Tegh Bahadur was the fifth and the youngest son of Guru Har Gobind and was born on first of April, 1621 to Mata Nanaki at Amritsar , Guru ke Mahal. He was married to Mata Gujri, daughter of Lal Chand of Kartarpur in Jullundhur district. After Guru Har Gobind, he with his mother, Mata Nanaki and his wife went to live in Bakala.

Makhan Shah’s discovery of the genuine Guru put an end to the pretensions of the false Gurus. Dhir Mal could not reconcile with the situation and was determined to snatch the Guruship by force. One day he communicated his feelings to his masand, Sihan who promised to put an end to his enemy (Guru). Accordingly the masand, along with a score of people, set forth to kill the Guru. He fired and the bullet struck Guru’s shoulder without serious wound who remained calm and full of composure. The other men plundered the property of the Guru and went away. When Makhan Shah heard of this incident, he proceeded with a body of Sikhs to Dhir Mal’s residence. Dhir Mal closed his doors but they burst it open and seized him and his accomplices, tied his masand’s hands at his back and brought them before the Guru. They brought back all the property of the Guru and they also took Dhir Mal’s property. They brought back the original copy of the Adi Granth which was in the possession of Dhir Mal and placed it before the Guru. The masand Sihan fell at the feet of the Guru and asked for forgiveness for his sins. The Guru pardoned the masand and ordered Makhan Shah to return all the property of Dhir Mal including the Adi Granth. He preached Makhan Shah and his other Sikhs that the holy Guru Nanak gave them the wealth of Nam which was sufficient for all their wants.

<br><br>GURU VISITS AMRITSAR:

<br><br>When Guru Har Gobind shifted his headquarters to Kiratpur, most of his disciples had also moved to that place with him and the Golden Temple at Amritsar fell ultimately into the hands of the impostors like Harji Minas. In November 1664, Guru Tegh Bahadur went to Amritsar . He bathed in the sacred tank but the Pujaris (or the ministrants) closed the doors of the Har Mandar against him. He saluted it and remarked that it was they who were rotten within, who through greed of offerings, had entered the temple. When the news spread, the people of Amritsar went in a body and poured their souls at his feet. The women of the city took the lead, welcome him with the Guru’s hymns and went with him singing all the way to the village Wadala (or Walla) where he stayed in the humble abode of a devout disciple. The Master blessed the women of Amritsar and Amritsar itself. On seeing their devotion he blessed them with these words,”God’s love and devotion shall ever abide among you.”

<br><br>FOUNDATION OF CITY OF ANANDPUR :

<br><br>Leaving Amritsar the Guru passed through the Majha and Malwa regions before reaching Kiratpur sometimes in May, 1665. He attended the last rites of Raja Dip Singh of Bilaspur and expressed his desire to build a new settlement near Kiratpur and also showed his inclination to buy a suitable land for that purpose. The Rani of Bilaspur offered to donate the site of Makhowal. The offer was accepted, a token price of about five hundred rupees was paid. The foundation stone of new settlement, Chak Nanaki was laid in June, 1665, after the revered name of Guru’s mother. In the course of time, a beautiful town called Anandpur grew up around it.



<h3>Sri Guru Gobind Singh Ji</h3>




It may not be out of the way to say here that throughout the annals of human history, there was no other individual who could be of more inspiring personality than Guru Gobind Singh. At its climax the tenth Nanak infused the spirit of both the saintlihood and the undauntedness in the minds and hearts of his followers to fight oppression in order to restore justice, righteousness (Dharma) and to uplift the down-trodden people in this world. It is said that after the martyrdom of Guru Tegh Bahadur, the tenth Master declared that he would create such a Panth (nation) which would not be cowed down by tyrant rulers but it would rather challenge the oppressor in every walk of life to restore justice, equality and peace for mankind. He further resolved that he would feel worthy to be called Gobind Singh only when any single member of his Khalsa Panth would successfully and undauntedly challenge the army of one hundred and twenty-five thousand opponents in the field. This point was rightfully proven at Chamkaur Sahib when Sahibzada Ajit Singh (Guru’s about 18 years old eldest son) challenged the Mughal forces and their allies, the hilly Rajas.

“The Divine Guru hath sent me for religion’s sake

On this account, I have come into the world;

Extend the faith everywhere

Seize and destroy the evil and sinful.

Understand this, ye holymen, in your minds

I assumed birth for the purpose of spreading the faith, saving the saints and extirpating all tyrants.”

<br><br>(Guru Gobind Singh- Chaupai, Bachitar Natak)



]]>
    </string>

    <string name="piare">The 5 Piare were as follows

\n\n1. Bhai Daya Singh Ji

\n\n2.Bhai Dharam Singh Ji

\n\n3.Bhai Himmat Singh Ji

\n\n4.Bhai Mohkam Singh Ji

\n\n5.Bhai Sahib Singh Ji

\n\nThere are various versions of how guru gobind singh ji made them 5 piare.

The one version is with the exception that Guru Ji took each ‘Pyara’ into the tent and came out of the tent brandishing a bloodstained sword. What happened in the tent is a mystery. The killing of goats is not an issue here.

The second version is very interesting and is a record of accounts that are supposedly eye-witnessed by a certain “Abu-ul-Turani”, who was under the employment of Emperor Aurangzeb. The Emperor had instructed him to keep a watchful eye on the Guru and act as the Emperor’s informer to keep him (the Emperor) informed of all the activities and movements of the Guru. The following is the version which ‘Abu-ul-Turani’ has narrated in his book or memoirs presumed to be held in the archives of the Aligarh University.

“The day Guru Gobind Singh prepared the nectar at ‘Anandpur’ the congregation was estimated to around thirty five to forty thousand sikhs who had come from far and wide. I had seen the grandeur of the ‘Mughal Darbars’ but this ‘Guru’s Darbar’ had a charm of its own – simply majestic and beyond comparison.

\n\nThe Guru came on the stage and after drawing his sword demanded a ‘head’ from the ‘Sangat’ present. This awesome call from the Guru sent a shiver to spines of the sikhs present in the congregation. Amidst all this a brave person emerged from the crowd and with his clasped hands humbly presented himself to the Guru. The Guru, with one stroke if his sword, beheaded the sikh in front of all the stunned ‘sangat’, and again asked for another ‘head’. Another person who came on the stage was similarly beheaded. The Guru made the eerie call again and simultaneously three devout sikhs came on the stage and met the same fate under the merciless sword of the Guru. The stage was a ghastly sight with the torsos and heads of the five drenched in pools of blood. All the trace of blood diminished after the Guru cleaned it with water. The Guru then medically joined each head on a different body and thereafter covered them with white sheets.

He then ordered a stone urn and on top of it he put an iron pot in which he added some water. He put his sword in it and started moving it, while chanting some words. He took some time and during this period some woman from the Guru’s household came and put something in the pot. The nectar (Abe-Hayat) was now ready. The Guru then removed the white sheets from one body and poured the nectar into the dead man’s mouth, on the hair and on the body. While he was performing this ritual he kept on pronouncing “Waheguru ji ka Khalsa, Waheguru ji ki Fateh”( The Khalsa belongs to the Almighty and to the Almighty is the victory ). To the amazement of the ‘sangat’, the person sat up and loudly chanted “Waheguru ji ka Khalsa, Waheguru ji ki Fateh”.

The whole congregation was aghast and taken aback by this miracle. The Guru did the same to the rest of the four bodies and they also like their counterpart rose up with shouts of “Waheguru ji ka Khalsa, Waheguru ji ki Fateh”. The Guru then took these five sikhs into a tent and after some time they emerged wearing new white clothes. The Guru then kneeled down in front of them and asked them to give him the life giving nectar. Obligingly they obeyed and baptized the Guru .

The Guru named them Daya Singh, Dharam Singh, Himmat Singh, Mohkam Singh and Sahib Singh and consequently changed his name from Gobind Rai to Gobind Singh. What happened in front of my eyes completely entranced me, and my heart longed to be in the Guru’s eternal feet. With a lump in my throat, I approached the Guru and begged him to baptize me and take me in his abode. The Guru smiled and baptized me and named me ‘Ajmer Singh’. Thus with the Guru’s blessing I attained absolute bliss. This was the last report I sent to Aurangzeb in which I mentioned that the Guru was not an ordinary person but was ‘Allah’ Himself. Furthermore I warned the Emperor that his enmity towards the Guru will lead to the downfall and destruction of the Mughal Empire.”

The above narration of ‘Abu-ul-Turani’ does carry considerable weight, but it requires more research and looking into . I appeal to our scholars and ‘prabandhak committees’ to explore this subject with interest and an impartial mind.</string>


    <string name="wadde">The eldest of the four sons of Guru Gobind Singh, Sahibzada Ajit Singh was born at Paunta sahib on 7th january 1687 A.D. Sahibzada Jujhar Singh the second son of the tenth Guru, was born in March 1689 A.D. at Anandpur Punjab. The two were aged 18 yrs and 16 yrs respectively when they achieved martyrdom at Chamkaur Sahib. Because of their heroic deeds at such a young age, Sikhs reverdly call them “Baba”, expressive of their highest regard and respect for these brave sons of the Guru..They underwent training in physical ftness,riding,and use of weapons apart from getting formal and religious (Gurmat) education from competent Sikhs and their father right from their childhood.

Guru Ji, accompanied by Sikhs and his family members evacuated Anandpur Sahib in December 1704 A.D. They had hardly reached the bank of rivulet Sirsa, when the enemy forces attacked them from behind without caring a bit about the promises made by them earlier in the name of their Holy Books.

Sahibzada Ajit Singh and part of Sikh forces kept the attacking enemy at bay by engaging them in a fierce battel till Guru Gobind Singh accompanied by others crossed the rivulet, which was in spate due to heavy rains upstream. Later Ajit Singh and the remaining Sikhs too crossed the rivulet sirsa and joined Guru Gobind Singh later. The enemy forces were deeply impressed by the fighting and leadership qualities shown by the eldest son of Guru Gobind Singh. The flooded rivlet took a heavy toll of Sikh lives.

By evening of the follwing day, Guru Gobind Singh accompanied by his only two elder sons and forty surviving Sikhs arrived at village Chamkaur, thoroghly exhausted. They quickly got themselves setteld in fort-like house of chaudhary Budhi Chand and decided to face the approching enemy forces there.

\n\nSAHIBZADA AJIT SINGH’S MARTYRDOM

\n\nWhen groups of Sikhs started going out of Garhi and fought bravely in afflicting heavy casualities before laying down their precious lives, Sahibzada Ajit Singh sought permission of his father to also allow him to go out to fight side by side the brave Sikhs.

Guru Gobind Singh was immensely pleased at this and embraced his son. He himself armed his son and sent him out with the next group of five Sikhs whom he considered no less dear than his own sons, to prove Guru’s saying that he would be worthy of being Gobind Singh when he would make a Sikh so brave and fearless that he would fight with one lakh and quarter enemies alone.

Guru Gobind Singh was watching the brave acts of his son in the battle field from the fortess. He had been keeping the enemy at bay by his arrows thus providing his son a chance for prolonged fight with the enemy soldiers.The Guru was immensly pleased at the courage shown by his son and the tactics employed by him for inflicting heavy casualties on the adversaries. Thus fell the brave son of the Great Guru providing inspiration to the Sikhs for generation to come. The Sikh community will keep remembering this young martyr son of the tenth master for all times to come.

\n\nSAHIBZADA JUJHAR SINGH’S MARTYRDOM

\n\nSahibzada Jujhar Singh, the second son of Guru Gobind Singh had been keenly observing from the fortess Chamkor the heroic fight put up by his elder brother, Sahibzada Ajit Singh against overwhelming number and better equipped enemy soldiers. The brave fight put up by his elder brother filled Sahibzada Jujhar Singh with happiness and courage.No sooner did Sahibzada Ajit Singh fell martyr, Sahibzada Jujhar Singh requested his dear father Guru Gobind Singh to grant him permission to accompany the next batch of Sikhs to repeat the heroic acts of his elder brother. He assured his father that he will not let him down and that he would attack the enemy soldiers and drive them away as a shepherd drives his flock of sheep.

The Guru Father was filled with immense pleasure at the determination of his 16 years old second son. He armed his son with weapons and allowed him to go out with next batch of five Sikhs.

Once outside the fortess, the young Jujhar Singh fearlessly attacked the enemy soldiers like a lion, while accompanying Sikhs formed a protective ring around him. Guru Gobind Singh was watching his brave son’s deeds of valour and appreciated his courage and swordsmanship from top of the fortess. Even the enemy soldiers could not help appreciating the ferocity and smartness of the young boy. They had never seen such bravery performed by anyone at such a young age against mighty enemy forces. Sahibzada Jujhar Singh using arrows spear and finally his sword felled numerous enemy soldiers. Headless bodies of enemy soldiers were piling up around him. The accompanying Sikhs were likewise putting to death many more enemy soldiers while keeping a protective ring around Sahibzada Jujhar Singh.

After a long drawn battle, the enemy soldiers attacked the young Jujhar Singh from all sides in large numbers, breaking the protective ring around him.Under the appreciative gaze of his father and the accompanying Sikhs, Sahibzada Jujhar Singh put up a brave fight but was ultimately fatally injured and fell martyr on the ground encircled by heaps of dead bodies of the enemy forces.

The way both the elder sons of Guru Gobind Singh achieved martyrdom upholding the principles for which their father had been actively mobilizing his disciples, the Guru was able to show to all the Sikhs and enemy the he did not value his own sons more than his Sikhs and that he would not hesitate even to sacrifice his own sons for the Sikh cause.

Thus, Guru Gobind Singh, sacrificed his dear and brave sons, only to prove that when it comes to making sacrifices for Sikh cause, he would not hesitate to offer his own sons to show to the world that the Sikh ideals alone, and not his own sons, were more dear to him.</string>


    <string name="chhote">Guru Gobind Singh ji decided to evacuate Anandpur Sahib, on the advice of his Sikhs, although he had no confidence on the promises made by the adversaries, and told them about his views. Guru ji, accompanied by Sikhs and his family members evacuated Anandpur Sahib in December 1704, A.D. They had hardly reached the bank of rivulet Sirsa, when the enemy forces attacked them from behind without caring a bit about the promises made by them earlier in the name of their Holy Books. During the ensuing battle on the bank of Sirsa rivulet which was in spate due to heavy rains upstream, only Guruji, forty Sikhs and two elder sons of Guru ji, Sahibzada Ajit Singh and Sahibzada Jujhar Singh, were able to safety cross the river.Others either died fighting bravely or were drowned in the flooded waters.

The two younger sons of the Guru, Sahibzada Zorawar Singh and Sahibzada Fateh Singh, accompanied by thier Grandmother Mata Gujri ji, strayed away walking along the bank of Sirsa, without making any attempt to cross it. While walking away from the scene of battle along the bank of rivulet Sirsa, they met their old servent named Gangu Brahmin, who had worked in their house for nearly 20 years. On his request, Mata Gujri, accompanied by his two grandsons, agreed to go with Gangu to his village and stay at his place for some time.

Mata Gujri ji was carrying good number of gold coins in those days. She kept the money under her pillow when she went to sleep in the house alongwith Sahibzada Zorawar Singh and Fateh Singh. Gangu’s greed for money turned him unfaithful.He quitly stole the money bag from under the pillow of Mata Gujri Ji while she was fast a sleep. When she got up in the morning she did not find the money bag under her pillow.She enquired from Gangu politely about the gold coins. The thief Gangu got annoyed at this questioning by Mata ji and started threatening her that he would get her arrested along with her grandsons for this accusation. Mata Ji tried to calm him down. Gangu had his eyes on the prize that he would receive from the Mughal rulers if he handed over the mother and two sons of Guru Gobind Singh to the police authorities. Accompanied by the village chief, he went to the police station at Morinda town and informed the station incharge about the preseence of Guru Gobind Singh’s mother and his two youger sons in his house and requested him to bestow him prize money for helping the authorities in the arrest of fugitives.

The police officer was immensly pleased at this important information provided by Gangu. He accompaind him to his vilage and arrested Mata Gujri along with her two grandsons and handed them over to Nawab Wazir Khan of Sirhand. Nawab Wazir Khan who had to return empty handed from Anandpur Sahib without being successful in arresting Guru Gobind Singh or his associates, was too glad to find Guru’s mother and two sons in his prison.

Mata ji along with her two grandsons was imprisoned in the cold tower at Sirhind.The Nawab ordered them to be produced in his court the next morning. Sitting on the floor of this cold tower on this very cold December night,Mata Gujri tried to provide comfort and warmth of her body to her grand sons putting them on her lap,and Kissing the foreheades of the beautiful Kids,went to sleep. She woke them up early the next morning and readying them for the ensuing test they were going to be put to at the court of Wazir Khan,the tyrant ruler of Sirhind.
She thus said to them, “O sons of great Guru Gobind Singh ! you are going to be offered all the comforts of a luxurious life if you agree to say goodbye to your religion and adopt Islam as your new religion.If you refuse to accept such an attractive offer they will threaten you with painful deaths.

\n\nI have full confidence that though you are young Kids,you will neither be fooled by the attractive offers nor be seduced by their threats. Be brave like your Guru father who has put every thing including his life at stake to prepare people to uproot the rule of tyrant rulers. Keep up the honour of your father at all costs.”

While the grandmother was still advising her grandsons, the soldiers of Wazir Khan arrived to take the two kids of Guru Gobind Singh to the court. Mata Gujri wished her grandsons and sent them with the soldiers praying for their success to uphold their principles and steadfastness at the court.

Many a senior officers and advisors of Nawab Wazir Khan were seated in the court along with him in addition to prominent public personalities. On entring the court Sahibzada Jorawar Singh and Sahibzada Fateh Singh loudly uttred, “Waheguru Ji Ka Khalsa, Waheguru Ji Ki Fateh” to the utter astonishment and amazement of Wazir Khan and his courtiers.

One of the prominent courtier Sucha Nand told the courageous sons of Guru Gobind Singh to bow before the ruler Wazir Khan and salute like the Muslims do. The kids told him that like other Sikhs, they too bow before no one except their Guru.

Nawab Wazir Khan now took over and said, “O small kids ! Your dad alongwith your two elder brothers has been killed in the battlefield. Luckily you have arrived in my court alive. Be quick and agree to be converted to Islam. As Muslim kids you will be provided best comforts of life like princes. You will be living in palaces, wearing silk clothes, eat variety of foods and play with other Muslim Princes and many servants will be at your beck and call, day and night.We are going to ban Sikhism and we will not leave any one alive as a Sikh. If you do not heed my advice to become Muslim, you will be put to the death in a most merciless manner. You will be cut to pieces so that no one dare become a Sikh in future.”

In reply to Wazir Khan’s lecture the brave kids said, “Sikhism is dearer to us than our lives. Nothing in this illusory world can induce us to shed our religion. We are kids of lion Guru Gobind Singh who is determind to infuse courage into the people of all religions to rise against the cruel and tyrant rulers to gain freedom. Our grandfather, Sri Guru Tegh Bahadur laid down his life to defend the right of religious freedom for the sake of opressed Hindu community being decimated by tyrant Aurangzeb

    \n\nOur great great grandfather, Sri Guru Arjun Dev Ji submitted gladly to the will of God while facing tortuons death under the orders of Emperor Jahangir, to infuse courage and endurance in his disciples rather than convert as Muslim. We will never bring bad name to the predecessor martyrs of our faith even if we have to face death.”

Those present in the court of Wazir Khan were greatly impressed by the brave reaction offerd to Wazir Khan by 6 yrs old Baba Fateh Singh and 8 yrs old Baba Zorawar Singh.

In order to offer some respite and encouragement to the dazed Wazir Khan, Sucha Nand courtier commented, “if these Kids at such an adolescent age can have courage to shun all inducements and threats to their lives, they could pose grave danger to the Mughal rulers when they grow upto manhood. Like their father they would encourage other Sikhs to rise in revolt against the Kingdom. It will be proper to deal with them firmly now and no mercy should de shown to them just because they are small children.

    \n\nNawab Wazir Khan, though impressed by the moral support provided and suggestions made by Sucha Nand, was more inclined towards coverting to Islam, the brave young sons of the great Guru Gobind Singh rather than punishing them with death penalty. He wanted to provide an opportunity to the historians to write that the two younger sons of Guru Gobind Singh preferred Islam to Sikhism. He, therfore controlled his anger and allowed the lads to go back home and consult their grandmother who might advise them to accept Islam to save their lives.

Saying this Wazir Khan hurriedly left the court there by adjourning it for the day and thus denying the lads an opportunity to give a benifitting reply to his latest suggestion.
Mata Gujri Ji was immensly pleased to see her grandsons back in high spirits heaving a sigh of relief. She took them hurriedlyfrom the soldiers into her bossem and kissed profusely their bright and smiling faces gave indications of their winning the battle for the day. thereafter, she asked and they told her about what happended in the court of Wazir Khan. They made a special mention about the wicked advice provided to the ruler of Sirhind by Sucha Nand Courtier.

</string>

    <string name="glossary">Adi Granth : the original name for the Guru Granth Sahib.

\n\nAhankar : false pride, one of the five evils a human can fall into. Pride in one’s possessions, intelligence, power or wealth takes one away from God and gives a false sense of superiority over others.

\n\nAkhand path : a complete, non-stop reading of the Guru Granth Sahib from beginning to end. This is usually undertaken in celebration for festivals and important events such as weddings and Khalsa baptisms. The reading begins two days before the event and is timed to coincide with the climax of the the festival. It may be carried out by relays of devout Sikhs, or by professional readers. It normally takes about 48 hours of continuous reading.

\n\nAmrit : this word carries many meanings. It is essentially sugar water, made in a ceremonial bowl at the gurdwara and stirred with a kirpan to sanctify it. The sugar water plays an important part in Sikh ceremonies; for example, it is scattered

over babies and traced onto their tongue during the naming ceremony, and used extensively during the initiation into the Khalsa (a ceremony also commonly known as ‘the amrit ceremony’. The literal translation of the word means ‘water of life’ or ‘holy water’.

\n\nAmritdhari : the full name for a Sikh who has been through the ceremony of initiation into the Sikh brotherhood of the Khalsa.

\n\nAmritsar : a town in Northern India where the Golden Temple sits on an island in the centre of a lake. This is the holiest place on earth for Sikhs, and the first place that the Adi Granth was installed in 1604.

\n\nArdas : the formal prayers recited by the congregation during a service at the gurdwara.

\n\nBaisakhi : the first month of the Sikh year, a celebration of new year and also the celebration of the formation of the Khalsa in 1699 by Guru Gobind Singh.

\n\nChuni : the large headscarf worn by Sikh women. It covers their head, neck and shoulders.

\n\nDiwali : the Festival of Lights, which is held in October/November and celebrates the foundation of Amritsar and the release of Guru Har Gobind (and 52 Hindu kings) from prison in the Gwalior Fort.

\n\nGranthi : the closest thing to a community leader of the Sikhs. This man (or man and wife team – never a woman on her own) leads the reading during services at the gurdwara, organises visits to anyone who is sick, teaches the children, arbitrates in arguments and officiates at ceremonies. There is a granthi in every gurdwara.

\n\nGurbani : the total sum of God’s scripture, set down in the Adi Granth by the Gurus. By reading and understanding the Gurbani, one can approach the understanding the Gurus had of the will and way of God.

\n\nGurdwara : this literally translates as ‘the door to the Guru’ and is the name of the religious centres used by Sikhs. A gurdwara acts as a community centre, teaching hall, meeting place and somewhere to hold religious ceremonies. The gurdwara also has a kitchen ( langar) where food is cooked and given freely to anyone who visits the gurdwara (also called langar). All Sikhs give a proportion of their income to the gurdwara so that the langar can continue to feed all who need to be fed. There are no chairs in the gurdwara; all who enter sit equally on the floor and lower than the Guru Granth Sahib, which rests on a special pedestal. Special seating is, however, always provided for disabled visitors.

\n\nGuru : a man blessed by God, who is born enlightened, without needing to learn how to be holy. Gu translates as ‘evil darkness’ and Ru as ‘divine light’; a guru is a man perfectly poised above good and evil, who has already transcended to another level. The name is commonly used for a religious teacher.

Guru Granth Sahib : the ever-living Guru and last of the lineage of Gurus. This Sikh holy book is a collection of the writings and scripture of the Gurus, gathered together in 1604 by the fifth human Guru, Guru Arjan, and published by the last Guru, Guru Gobind Singh (with a few additions). It lays out the way of life for a Sikh.

\n\nHarmandir : the Golden Temple in Amritsar , which is the holiest place on earth for the Sikh nation. The first copy of the Guru Granth Sahib was installed here in 1604, and people from all over the world still travel here to bathe in the waters of the beautiful lake that surrounds the Temple , and to cross the causeway to it in order to listen to readings from the book. People dip into the holy water with faith that their impurities will be washed away – an act that is known as dukh bhanjan, and means to conquer illness.

Hukamnama/ Hukam : God’s will. Readings in the gurdwara often go by the name of Hukamnama, which translates as ‘Royal order’ – this is literally the direct decree of God as given to the Gurus and laid down in their writings in the Guru Granth Sahib and other texts.

\n\nKaam (kam) : lust. One of the five moral evils of Sikhism, tempting people away from God and disrupting the smooth order of society and relationships.

\n\nKach (kaccha, kacchera) : the long pants worn by Sikh men and women as a symbol of their physical and spiritual purity and chastity. They are one of the five Ks of the Khalsa and should not be removed unless absolutely necessary.

\n\nKaur : translates literally as ‘Princess’. This is the name given to a female Sikh during her naming ceremony to signify that she is part of the family of Sikhs.

\n\nKesh : the long, uncut hair (this includes beard and body hair as well as the hair on the head) of a Sikh. It symbolises the higher consciousness attained by the Khalsa, and is tied in a special knot before being covered with a turban (the crown of spirituality). Young boys wear their hair tied up and covered with a keski or small turban, whereas girls wear their hair long and loose. Married women tend to plait their hair. You may see older men wearing a hairnet on their beard as well to help keep it under control. Sikhs do not cut any of their hair.

\n\nKeski : a small, informal turban worn by male Sikhs when they are in private, at home relaxing.

\n\nKhalsa Panth : the full name for the Brotherhood of baptised Sikhs – those wh have gone through the amrit ceremony of initiation and now wear the five Ks and live according to the Gurbani of the Gurus. This ceremony was first performed by Guru Gobind Singh, who was the last of the human Gurus, in 1699. It translates as ‘Community of Pure Ones’.

\n\nKangha : the wooden comb that is used to smooth the long hair ( kesh) and take the tangles out. It is tucked into the turban and carried at all times. It symbolises spiritual and physical cleanliness and the consequent smoothing of the way. It is another of the five Ks.

\n\nKirpan : the small sword worn by baptised Sikhs as one of the five Ks. Their right to carry this weapon is covered by the Race Relations Act, and it is a symbol of their willingness to fight in defence of what they believe in and the continued fight against evil. A kirpan is essentially a long knife with a double-edged blade and usually a decorated handle, and is worn beneath the clothing.

\n\nKrodh : another of the five evils that beset humanity and divert their attention away from God. This is anger and harms not only the person feeling it, but potentially others as well.

\n\nKutha/jhatka : the name given to meat slaughtered in a way that is appropriate for another religion (such as halal or kosher). At the time the Sikh religion was established, Sikhs were under intense persecution from Muslims and Hindus, and – along with the desire to concentrate on the practice of faith rather than following the rituals – this desire to break free of other faiths included not eating meat prepared for them.

\n\nLangar : the name for both the kitchen that is found in every gurdwara and the meals that a community shares there. The food in the langar is provided from the money that every Sikh gives to the gurdwara. Meals are vegetarian and served freely to anyone who visits the gurdwara – whether they are a Sikh or non-Sikh, king or leper. They are usually eaten in groups, sitting on the floor; the idea is that no one is above anyone else, and that everyone has a right to share a meal in good company.

\n\nLobh : greed, another of the five evils of humanity. It makes a person self-centred, causes jealousy and can lead them into falsehood and theft.

\n\nMoh : over-attachment to worldly things, relationships and possessions. Such attachments blind the individual to the attachment they should have to God, and so is one of the evils of humanity.

\n\nMoral evils : the Sikhs believe in five basic evils that lie at the root of most human misery. These are kaam (lust), ahankar (pride), moh (attachment), krodh (anger) and lobh (greed). They can all be overcome by practising the eight virtues and living a life of contemplation on the infinite good of God.

\n\nNaam karan : the naming ceremony for newborn Sikh babies. The Guru Granth Sahib is opened at random, and the first letter on the left-hand page is taken as the first letter of the child’s name. They also adopt ‘ kaur’ or ‘ Singh’ as part of their name, signifying their entry into the Sikh community.

\n\nPanch kakkars : the proper name for the ‘five Ks’, so called because their Punjabi names all begin with a ‘K’. These are the outward symbols of a baptised Sikh’s commitment to following the way of the Waheguru.

\n\nPath : the liturgical reading of the Guru Granth Sahib. On special occasions the book is read non-stop from cover to cover by relays of people ( akhand path ). At other times, it can be read over seven days (for example, as part of the funeral and mourning period) or greater periods of time. All ordered reading of the book is called path.

\n\nParshad : part of every ceremony that takes place at the gurdwara involves the distribution of prashad. This is a sweet pudding made of flour, sugar and ghee (clarified butter) that has been blessed and is shared as a sign of community. People who are sick in hospital will have prashad brought to them to maintain their links with their community.

\n\nReht maryada : the official Sikh Code of Conduct. It is not a spiritual guide as such, but rather a codified handbook on how to be a good Sikh. It was first drawn up in the 1930s as the Sikh community began to move out of Punjab and into the rest of the world, and covers every aspect of behaviour from how to cremate the dead to how to pray.

\n\nSalwar : the long trousers and tunic worn by many Sikh women. It covers their arms and legs and does not reveal their body shape, but is still practical. The salwar is worn with the chuni – a headscarf that is wrapped around the head and neck and covers the shoulders as well.

\n\nSangat : this word is used generally to refer to any gathering of Sikhs to listen to a Guru, whether that be listening to the Guru Granth Sahib being read at the gurdwara, or a group of people listening to the teachings of a human guru.

\n\nSehjdhari : the term that is used to describe sikhs (with a lower-case ‘s’) that have not undergone initiation into the Khalsa brotherhood by baptism (going through the amrit ceremony). Baptism is not allowed unless the granthi can be sure that the initiate is fully aware of the commitment they are about to undertake, and its implications. Because of this, there are many Sikhs – not just children and teenagers – who have not been fully initiated.

\n\nSingh : translates as ‘lion’; this is the name adopted by male Sikhs, in the same way as Kaur is a female name. It is given to a child when they are named at the gurdawara a few weeks after their birth.

\n\nTurban : a head cover worn by male Sikhs to cover their kesh or long hair. It is made from a long piece of cotton cloth, wound in a particular manner around the head. A new one is prepared every day, and it is rarely removed voluntarily, being the ‘crown of the spirit’. A male child is taken to the gurdwara at about 11 or 12 years of age to undergo a simple ceremony at which his first turban is tied onto his head.

\n\nVirtues : Sikhs have five moral evils that are traits in themselves and that they try to overcome. They do this by practising the eight virtues: gyan (wisdom), niaon (justice), santokh (temperance), himmat (courage), sat (truthful living), dhiraj (patience), sabar (contentment) and namarta (humility).

\n\nWaheguru : the ‘Wonderful Lord’; one of the names of God.


    </string>
</resources>




