<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Sikhism Knowledge</string>

    <string name="navigation_drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>

    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>

    <string name="golden_temple_string">Sri Harmandir Sahib or Golden Temple, (on account of its scenic beauty and golden coating for English speaking world), is named after Hari(God) the temple of God. The Sikhs all over the world, daily wish to pay visit to Sri Amritsar and to pay obeisance at Sri Harmandir Sahib in their Ardas.
    \n\n"SIKHAN NOO SIKHI DAN, KES DAN, REHAT DAN, BIBEK DAN, BHAROSA DAN, DANAN SIR DAN NAAM DAN, SRI AMRITSAR JI DE DARSHAN ISHNAN"
    \n\nIt is our request, Waheguru Ji, that Sikhs should have your grace to keep ‘Sikhi’, the hair(Kes), all the ‘Rehats’ (the commandments given by Guru Gobind Singh Ji), high intelligence, trustworthiness, and above all the supreme gift of remembering Your Name; they may be given the pleasure of visiting Amritsar.
    \n\n{ (Meaning Of Above Ardaas(Sikh Prayer) lines }
    \n\nGuru Arjan Sahib, the Fifth Nanak, conceived the idea of creating a central place of worship for the Sikhs and he himself designed the architecture of Sri Harmandir Sahib. Earlier the planning to excavate the holy tank (Amritsar or Amrit Sarovar ) was chalked out by Guru Amardas Sahib, the Third Nanak, but it was executed by Guru Ramdas Sahib under the supervision of Baba Budha ji. The land for the site was acquired by the earlier Guru Sahibs on payment or free of cost from the Zamindars (landlords) of native villages. The plan to establish a town settlement was also made. Therefore, the construction work on the Sarovar(the tank) and the town started simultaneously in 1570. The work on both projects completed in 1577 A.D.
    \n\nGuru Arjan Sahib got its foundation laid by a muslim saint Hazrat Mian Mir ji of Lahore on 1st of Magh, 1644 Bikrmi Samvat(December,1588). The construction work was directly supervised by Guru Arjan Sahib himself and he was assisted by the prominent Sikh personalities like Baba Budha ji, Bhai Gurdas ji, Bhai Sahlo ji and many other devoted Sikhs.
    \n\nUnlike erecting the structure on the higher level(a tradition in Hindu Temple architecture), Guru Arjan Sahib got it built on the lower level and unlike Hindu Temples having only one gate for the entrance and exit, Guru Sahib got it open from four sides. Thus he created a symbol of new faith, Sikhism. Guru Sahib made it accessible to every person without any distinction of Caste, creed, sex and religion.
    \n\nThe building work completed in 1601 A.D. on Bhadoon Sudi 1st, 1661 Bikrmi Samvat (August/September,1604). Guru Arjan Sahib installed newly created Guru Granth Sahib, in Sri Harmandir Sahib and appointed Baba Budha ji as its first Granthi i.e. the reader of Guru Granth Sahib. After this event it attained the status of ‘Ath Sath Tirath’. Now the Sikh Nation had their own Tirath, a pilgrimage center.
    \n\nSri Harmandir Sahib, is built on a 67ft. square platform in the centre of the Sarovar(tank). The temple itself is 40.5ft. square. It has a door each on the East, West, North and South. The Darshani Deori (an arch) stands at the shore end of the causeway. The door frame of the arch is about 10ft in height and 8ft 6inches in breath. The door panes are decorated with artistic style. It opens on to the causeway or bridge that leads to the main building of Sri Harmandir Sahib. It is 202 feet in length and 21 feet in width.

    \n\nThe bridge is connected with the 13 feet wide ‘Pardakshna’ (circumambulatory path). It runs round the main shrine and it leads to the ‘Har ki Paure’ (steps of God). On the first floor of ‘Har ki Paure’, there is continuous reading of Guru Granth Sahib.

   \n \nThe main structure of Sri Harmandir Sahib, functionally as well as technically is a three-storied one. The front, which faces the bridge, is decorated with repeated cusped arches and the roof of the first floor is at the height of the 26 feet and 9 inches.
   \n \nAt the top of the first floor 4 feet high parapet rises on all the sides which has also four ‘Mamtees’ on the four corners and exactly on the top of the central hall of the main sanctuary rises the third story. It is a small square room and have three gates. A regular recitation of Guru Granth Sahib is also held there.

    \n\nOn the top of this room stands the low fluted ‘Gumbaz’(dome) having lotus petal motif in relief at the base inverted lotus at the top which supports the ‘Kalash’ having a beautiful ‘Chhatri’ at the end.

    \n\nIts architecture represents a unique harmony between the Muslims and the Hindus way of construction work and this is considered the best architectural specimens of the world. It is often quoted that this architecture has created an independent Sikh school of architecture in the history of art in India.

    \n\nContinue Reading about Golden Temple’s Art and Architecture , Jalau ,Maryada and contribution of Maharaja Ranjit Singh</string>
    <string name="Martyrdom">Timeline of Martyrdom Week when Wadde Sahibzaade Sahibzada Ajit Singh ji,Sahibzada Jujhaar Singh Ji, and Chhotte Sahibzaade
        Sahibzada Zorawar Singh Ji and Sahibzada Fateh Singh ji got shaheedi at Chamkaur
        Sahib and Fatehgarh Sahib respectively.
\n\n* ਸ਼ਹੀਦੀ ਹਫਤਾ *
\n\n20 ਦਸੰਬਰ ਤੋਂ 27 ਦਸੰਬਰ ਤੱਕ

\n\n6 ਪੋਹ /20 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਸਵੇਰੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਨੇ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਸਮੇਤ ਅਨੰਦਪੁਰ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਦਾ ਕਿਲਾ ਛੱਡਿਆ ।

\n\n6 ਪੋਹ /20 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਦੀ ਰਾਤ ਗੁਰੂ ਜੀ ਅਤੇ ਵਡੇ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦੇ ਕੋਟਲਾ ਨਿਹੰਗ ਰੋਪੜ ਵਿਖੇ ਨਿਹੰਗ ਖਾਂ ਕੋਲ ਰਹੇ

\n\nਛੋਟੇ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦੇ ਅਤੇ ਮਾਤਾ ਗੁਜਰੀ ਜੀ ਕੁੰਮੇ ਮਾਸ਼ਕੀ ਦੀ ਝੁਗੀ ਵਿਚ ਰਹੇ

\n\n7 ਪੋਹ/21 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਗੁਰੂ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਅਤੇ ਵਡੇ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦੇ ਸ਼ਾਮ ਤੱਕ ਚਮਕੌਰ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਪਹੁੰਚੇ

\n\nਛੋਟੇ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦੇ ਅਤੇ ਮਾਤਾ ਗੁਜਰੀ ਜੀ ਨੂੰ ਗੰਗੂ ਬ੍ਰਾਹਮਣ ਆਪਣੇ ਪਿੰਡ ਖੇੜੀ ਲੈ ਗਿਆ

\n\n8 ਪੋਹ/ 22 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਚਮਕੋਰ ਗੜੀ ਦੀ ਜੰਗ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋਈ ਬਾਬਾ ਅਜੀਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਜੀ ਉਮਰ 17 ਸਾਲ ਭਾਈ ਮੋਹਕਮ ਸਿੰਘ (ਪੰਜਾ ਪਿਆਰਿਆਂ ਵਿਚੋਂ ) ਅਤੇ 7 ਹੋਰ ਸਿੰਘਾ ਨਾਲ ਸ਼ਹੀਦ ਹੋਏ

\n\nਬਾਬਾ ਜੁਝਾਰ ਸਿੰਘ ਉਮਰ 14 ਸਾਲ ਭਾਈ ਹਿੰਮਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਅਤੇ ਭਾਈ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਸਿੰਘ (ਪੰਜਾ ਪਿਆਰਿਆਂ ਵਾਲੇ ) ਅਤੇ ਤਿੰਨ ਹੋਰ ਸਿੰਘਾਂ ਸਮੇਤ ਸ਼ਹੀਦ ਹੋਏ ਅਤੇ

\n\n8 ਪੋਹ / 22 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਨੂੰ ਹੀ ਮੋਰਿੰਡੇ ਦੇ ਚੋਧਰੀ ਗਨੀ ਖਾਨ ਅਤੇ ਮਨੀ ਖਾਨ ਮਾਤਾ ਗੁਜਰ ਕੌਰ ਜੀ ਅਤੇ ਛੋਟੇ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਗੰਗੂ ਦੇ ਘਰੋਂ ਗ੍ਰਿਫਤਾਰ ਕਰਕੇ ਤੁਰ ਪਏ

\n\n9 ਪੋਹ / 23 ਦਿਸੰਬਰ : ਨੂੰ ਰਾਤ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਤੜਕ ਸਾਰ ਗੁਰੂ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਸਿੰਘਾ ਦੇ ਹੁਕਮ ਅੰਦਰ ਚਮਕੋਰ ਦੀ ਗੜੀ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਨਿਕਲ ਗਏ

\n\n9 ਪੋਹ /23 ਦਿਸੰਬਰ : ਦੀ ਰਾਤ ਦਸ਼ਮੇਸ਼ ਜੀ ਨੇ ਮਾਛੀਵਾੜੇ ਦੇ ਜੰਗਲ ਵਿੱਚ ਅਤੇ ਦਾਦੀ ਸਮੇਤ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦਿਆਂ ਨੇ ਸਰਹਿੰਦ ਦੇ ਠੰਡੇ ਬੁਰਜ ਵਿਚ ਗੁਜਾਰੀ

\n\n10 ਅਤੇ 11 ਪੋਹ/ 24 ਅਤੇ 25 ਦਸੰਬਰ : ਦੋ ਦਿਨ ਸਾਹਿਬਜ਼ਾਦਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਰਹਿੰਦ ਦੇ ਸੂਬੇ ਨਵਾਬ ਵਜ਼ੀਰ ਖਾਨ ਦੀ ਕਚਹਿਰੀ ਵਿਚ ਪੇਸ਼ ਕੀਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਅਤੇ

\n\nਪਿਤਾ ਦਸ਼ਮੇਸ਼ ਜੀ ਉੱਚ ਦੇ ਪੀਰ ਬਣ ਪਿੰਡ ਆਲਮਗੀਰ ਤੱਕ ਸਫਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਰਹੇ

\n\n12 ਪੋਹ / 26 ਦਸੰਬਰ: ਬਾਬਾ ਜ਼ੋਰਾਵਰ ਸਿੰਘ ਉਮਰ 7 ਸਾਲ ਅਤੇ ਬਾਬਾ ਫਤਿਹ ਸਿੰਘ ਉਮਰ 5 ਸਾਲ ਸੀ ਦੋਵੇਂ ਨੀਹਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਚਿਣ ਕੇ ਸ਼ਹੀਦ ਕੀਤੇ ਗਏ।

\n\nਮਾਤਾ ਗੁਜਰ ਕੌਰ ਜੀ ਠੰਢੇ ਬੁਰਜ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਵਾਸ ਤਿਆਗ ਗਏ।

\n\n13 ਪੋਹ ./ 27 ਦਸੰਬਰ ਨੂੰ ਤਿੰਨਾ ਦਾ ਦੇਹ ਸਸਕਾਰ ਸਤਿਕਾਰ ਯੋਗ ਮੋਤੀ ਰਾਮ ਮਹਿਰਾ ਅਤੇ ਟੋਡਰ ਮੱਲ ਨੇ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਕੀਤਾ ।</string>

    <string name="whether">Qazi and maulvis got together and began discussing religion.
A great fantasy has been created and no one could understood its mystery.
They asked Baba Nanak to open and search in his book whether Hindu is great or the Muslim.
Baba replied to the pilgrim hajis, that, without good deeds both will have to weep and wail.
Only by being a Hindu or a Muslim one can not get accepted in the court of the Lord.
As the colour of safflower is impermanent and is washed away in water, likewise the colours of religiosity are also temporary.
(Followers of both the religions) In their expositions, denounce Ram and Rahim. The whole of the world is following the ways of Satan
– Taken from a Shabad by Bhai Gurdaas Ji in Vaars Bhai Gurdaas</string>


    <string name="guru"> After Guru Ramdas had taken the gurgaddi he still continued doing lot of physical sewa. Once Baba Sri chand , son of Guru Nanak ji decided to meet Guru Ramdas ji. As soon as the word traveled to Ramdas ji, Guru Ramdas sent his followers to meet Sri Chand ji at the edge of the city and himself left his sewa to meet him. When Baba Sri Chand saw guru Ramdas he was shocked because with his yogic eyes he saw his father Guru Nanak in Guru Ramdas ji. He proclamed you are the image of my father .. you have the light of my father, but your beard is much longer than my father! why is your beard so long ?? Guru Ramdas ji answered – my beard is so long so that I can wipe the feet of the saints like u and he actually bent over to rub over Sri Chand’s feet. This surprised Sri Chand ji who jumped back and said even after so many years of ‘tap’ I have’nt been able to achieve this grace and humility. I have never seen such humility beofre. you are the king. you sit on the throne. you are the king of the yoga. They both enjoyed the meeting after that.
    ” With the rising of the sun, the Gurmukh speaks of the Lord. All through the night, he dwells upon the Sermon of the Lord. My God has infused this longing within me; I seek my Lord God. ||/||
    My mind is the dust of the feet of the Holy. The Guru has implanted the Sweet Name of the Lord, Har, Har, within me. I dust the Guru’s Feet with my hair. ||/||Pause|| – GGS ji pg:1355
    Soon the word spread that Sri Chand ji declared Ramdas ji as the yoga king.. the yogi’s stated to question what yoga does he knows and what is the throne he sits on ???.. so when they came to Guru Ramdas ji, ramdas ji told them to chant gods name instead of ausetrities and stop violence against their body, and instead of going to caves and leaving everything, live in your “grisht ashram” (homes) and bring moderation to your eating, sleeping and to your sensuality ..don’t deny yourself as a human but bring moderation to it and infuse yourself with moral courage ( sahaj yoga) and by these things they will gain union with god.. the way of yoga the celebs have adopted had actually seperated them from god for when they came close/in presence of a woman their equilibrum was disturbed bcos they were still humans.. Guru Ramdas told them to keep their equilibrium day and night by meditation and chanting gods name. and focusing on gods feet.
    You may pluck the strings with your hand, O Yogi, but your playing of the harp is in vain.
    Under Guru’s Instruction, chant the Glorious Praises of the Lord, O Yogi, and this mind of yours shall be
    imbued with the Lord’s Love. ||/||
    O Yogi, give your intellect the Teachings of the Lord.
    The Lord, the One Lord, is pervading throughout all the ages; I humbly bow down to Him. ||/||Pause|| You sing in so many Ragas and harmonies, and you talk so much, but this mind of yours is only playing a game
    You work the well and irrigate the fields, but the oxen have already left to graze in the jungle. ||2||
    In the field of the body, plant the Lord’s Name, and the Lord will sprout there, like a lush green field. O mortal, hook up your unstable mind like an ox, and irrigate your fields with the Lord’s Name, through the Guru’s Teachings. P||
    The Yogis, the wandering Jangams, and all the world is Yours, O Lord. According to the wisdom which You give them, so do they follow their ways.
    O Lord God of servant Nanak, O Inner-knower, Searcher of hearts, please link my mind to You. ||¥||9||6/||
    – GGS ji pg:368
    He further explained.. yoga is acceptance of both polarities ..good and bad .. when there is no good no bad .. ( kaun bhale ko mande) ?? when u accept all of it as god then you merge with god in ecstacy. and this is true yoga
    </string>

    <string name="Golden">The path from Town Hall to Golden Temple will be a heritage walk for all visitors. From Baba Saheb Ambedkar Statue to Maharaja Ranjit Singh, From Martyred Singhs to Festival Timings, the walk will take you in different eras before you reach the Golden Temple Complex</string>
    <string name="A">There’s a story about a saint who lived in his own anand, he cared about everyone and everyone loved him. Another blessed man also lived in the same town. One day a childless woman went to see the blessed man, she said , ‘Ask your God to grant me a son’. The Blessed man went to the top of the mountain and spoke to God of the poor woman’s request. He came back and told the lady, ‘God said that there are no children in your destiny’.

A few days later, the woman came back full of joy and happiness, she was giving sweets to one and all, the blessed man asked what she was celebrating. She replied, ‘The Saint has said I will be blessed with a beautiful baby boy, my dreams have come true!’.

The blessed man couldn’t understand it, he climbed the mountain and asked God ‘O Lord You said the lady had no children in her destiny, yet the saint has granted her a son. How can he overrule your decision?’ God replied, ‘O Blessed Man, before I answer that, go to the town and tell my children’s (villagers) that God wants a pound of their flesh.’

The Blessed Man spent the next few days telling everyone, they looked at him and ran away, no-one was prepared to give a pound of flesh. Then the Saint met him and he told him of the strange request to which the saint replied, ‘O Blessed Man, go back to God and ask him from which part of my body he wants it from.’

On top of the mountain the blessed man said to God, ‘Only the saint was prepared to obey your command, Lord. Even I was scared to obey it.’ God then answered him, ‘My Saint is prepared to die for me, I am bound by what he says. My saint can overturn destiny, everything belongs to the saint.’</string>
    <string name="bibi">“When the Mughal forces laid siege around Anandpur Sahib, many Singhs deserted the Guru, including the 40 Singhs who later became the 40 Muktas. Guru Gobind Singh Jee asked Bibi Basant Kaur if she wanted to leave the fort, as there would be terrible hardships in the coming months. However Bibi Jee politely declined, saying that she would not leave her Guru whatever the circumstances.

After some months of real difficulties and hunger, Guru Gobind Singh Jee decided to leave Anandpur Sahib at the request of his Sikhs. Evading the Mughal forces, the Guru and his Sikhs reached the River Sirsa. It was the winter months, and due to the cold weather and fast flowing river current, the Sikhs got scattered. Guru Gobind Singh Jee, Sahibzada Ajit Singh and Sahibzada Jujhar Singh got separated from Mata Gujjer Kaur ( Mata Gujri), Sahibzada Zorawar Singh and Sahibzada Fateh Singh.

Bibi Basant Kaur was with Mata Gujjer Kaur at this critical time, leading Mata Jee’s horse through the River Sarsa. Mata Jee’s horse led her to the other side of the river, but Bibi Basant Kaur got swept away by the cold but rapidly flowing river water. As the river carried her for some distance, she fell unconscious due to the horrendously cold water. Finally her body was washed up on the side of the riverbank.

A Mughal soldier, Samund Khan, seeing Bibi Basant Kaur unconscious, took advantage of her vulnerability and took her to his house. When she regained her consciousness, he asked her to accept Islam and become his wife. He said if she accepted his wishes, she would have all the material pleasures that she could ever dream of. Bibi Jee replied: “I could have left my Guru months ago and not had to endure such hardships at Anandpur Sahib. I will never leave my Guru.” Samund Khan was taken aback by Bibi Jee’s response, but thought leaving her locked up and hungry in a cell for some days would easily break her resolve.

Bibi Basant Kaur’s health was already in a bad state, but throughout her stay in the cell, she resolved to make Gurbani her Aasra. She sat cross-legged in one spot, but with deep concentration and faith in Waheguroo, she kept doing Sukhmani Sahib da Paath. No fears about the future could remove her concentration from Guru Jee and Gurbani.

When Samund Khan came to Bibi Jee after eight days, her resolve was nowhere near broken. This left Samund Khan seething with anger. Evil thoughts crossed his mind. He started to move towards Bibi Jee. Bibi Jee realised the situation, and started praying to Kalgidhaar Dasmesh Pita.

Samund Khan was saying in an antagonising and sarcastic manner “what’s your Guru going to do for you now? Are you ready to accept Islam now?” Bibi Jee responded “My Guru is always with me. You cannot do anything to me.” “Don’t lie … your Guru is nowhere to be seen,” he said in a taunting manner, as he moved further towards Bibi Jee. Bibi Jee started to do Ardaas to Guru Sahib with even greater pyaar and faith. Suddenly, out of nowhere, Bibi Jee said “My Guru is here.” He was now within touching distance of Bibi Jee. He said, “I cannot see him … you’re imagining things.” Bibi Jee said, “you will not be able to see him … you’re a Paapi person, full of the 5 vices. Only those with high Kamayee can see him. My Guru Jee is here with me.”

“gur maerai sa(n)g sadh aa hai n aalae || simar simar this sadhaa samh aalae ||1|| rehaao ||”

My Guru is always with me, near at hand. Meditating, meditating in remembrance on Him, I cherish Him forever. ||7||Pause|| – Guru Granth Sahib Ji Pg 394

At this instance, Samund Khan tried to move further towards Bibi Jee, yet his body had now frozen. Although he could see with his eyes and speak with his mouth, all his body’s muscle had frozen, as if he was a statue. Bibi Jee had realised what her Guru Jee had done. She asked, “I thought you said my Guru would not save me? I thought you said he was not here?”

After a few minutes of being frozen like a statue, he started begging Bibi Jee to do Ardaas to unfreeze him. Bibi Jee said that her Ardaas would only happen if Samund Khan promised to be a decent God-fearing person. Samund Khan readily agreed. Bibi Jee did her Ardaas, and Guru Gobind Singh Jee unfroze the Mughal soldier. For the following few weeks, having seen the Kamayee and Gursikhi Jeevan of Bibi Basant Kaur, he served Bibi Jee very well whilst Bibi Jee continued doing Bhagti. He then took Bibi Jee personally to Dina Kangoor to re-unite Bibi Jee with Guru Gobind Singh Jee.

What can we learn from this episode?

Guru Jee is always with us, but only those fortunate souls with high Bhagti and Naam Jeevan realise this. Such souls can speak, feed, see and call upon their Guru all the time and at any time.

If we are to reach this stage, we must have full faith in the Guru, incorporate his teachings into our lives and never leave the Guru … just like Bibi Basant Kaur Jee.

If we become Bhagats of Waheguroo, Waheguroo will always preserve our honour, saving us physically whilst having mortal form and saving us forever once our soul leaves the body.</string>
    <string name="bhagat">“Jin Prem Kiyo Tin Hi Prabh Paayo” – Guru Gobind Singh ji => Pure Love Leads to God

Trilochan awoke early daily just to have sight of Namdev,

Together they would concentrate on the Lord and Namdev would tell him the grand stories of God.

(Trilochan asked Namdev) “kindly pray for me so that if the Lord accepts, I may also have a glimpse of His blessed vision.”

Namdev asked Thakur, the Lord, as to how Trilochan could have sight of the Lord ? The Lord God smiled and explained to Naamdev;

“No offerings are needed by me. Out of my delight only, I would make Trilochan to have sight of me. ”

i am under the total control of the devotees and their loving claims i can never reject; rather I myself also cannot understand them.

Their loving devotion, in fact, becomes mediator and makes them meet me.”

– Bhai Gurdaas Ji in Vaars Bhai Gurdaas on Pannaa 10</string>

    <string name="the">There is a Sakhi (historic event) about a great Sant Sipahee.(Saint-Soldier).. he truly had attained one-ness with Waheguru ji and had mastered weaponary too. In the battlefield he fought for justice. His opponent had been overpowered and lay on his back on the floor. The Sant-sipahee was about to destroy the sinner by plunging the sword of Akal into his chest, when the opponent spat in the Sant-Sipahee’s face.

The Sant-Sipahee’s blood boiled, rage and fury burned him for a moment, he raised his sword with new fervour.but stopped the sword in mid-swing!. The enemy was shocked, expecting to be dead, he grunted ‘Kill Me Sikh, you have beaten me’.

The Sant-Sipahee replied, ‘Before I was fighting for justice, against the evil actions of your army, and destroying you was destroying injustice . When you spat in my face I wanted to kill you because you insulted ME. I was going to kill you out of ANGER AND HATE which would have been wrong and against the principle of Sikhi/Khalsa. I would have to have been reborn because of that, so I have spared you’.

The enemy soldier was so incredibly amazed at the Khalsa soldier, that within a few months he left his troops and joined the Khalsa.

Criticise and Punish the Actions,

Love the Person…… It’s a hard path to follow …. finer than a hair and

sharper than a sword .

“Kabeera, janaa gyan tah Dharam hai jahaa jhooth tah paap” – (Guru Granth Sahib Ji) Kabeer, where there is spiritual wisdom, there is righteousness and Dharma. Where there is falsehood, there is sin.
    </string>

    <string name="faq">WHAT IS THE DEFINITION OF A SIKH?
\n\nThe most widely accepted definition of a Sikh comes from the Sikh code of conduct, the Rehat Maryada. Originally written in Punjabi, it is translated as:
“A Sikh is any woman or man whose faith consists of belief in:
One God,
The ten Gurus, from Guru Nanak to Guru Gobind Singh,
The Guru Granth Sahib,
The utterances and teachings of the ten Gurus,
Who has faith in and aspires to take Amrit, initiation ceremony into the Khalsa,
And who does not owe allegiance to any other religion.”
As with most religions, however, a devotee cannot be confined to a definition.

\n\nHOW MANY SIKHS LIVE IN THE UNITED STATES? WHEN DID SIKHS FIRST IMMIGRATE TO AMERICA?
\n\nThere are over 500,000 Sikh Americans, and Sikhs have been in America for over 100 years.

\n\nWHY DON’T PEOPLE KNOW ABOUT SIKHISM EVEN THOUGH IT IS THE 5TH LARGEST WORLD RELIGION?
\n\nThere are several different reasons. First, Sikhism, compared to other world traditions, is relatively young. The faith first emerged in 1469. Second, since many people are not aware that Sikhism is the fifth largest world religion, it is not referenced when discussing the other world religions. For example, many school textbooks have incorrect or no information on the faith.

\n\nIS THERE AN OFFICIAL SIKH GREETING?
\n\nThe tenth Sikh Guru instructed Sikhs to greet each other with “Waheguru ji ka Khalsa, Waheguru ji ki Fateh” (“The Khalsa belongs to Waheguru (the Divine) and victory belongs to Waheguru”). Another common Sikh greeting is “Sat Sri Akal” (“Truth reigns eternal”).

\n\nIS THERE A SIKH EMBLEM OR SYMBOL? WHAT IS THE HISTORICAL SIGNIFICANCE OF THE KHANDA?
\n\nThe Ik Onkar and the Khanda are some of the symbols of the Sikhs. According to the Sikh scholar Kapur Singh, the Khanda first appeared around the eighteenth century.
“The Khanda is the symbol of the Sikhs, as the Cross is to Christians or the Star of David is to Jews. It reflects some of the fundamental concepts of Sikhism. The symbol derives its name from the double-edged sword (also called a Khanda) which appears at the center of the logo. This double-edged sword is a metaphor of divine knowledge, its sharp edges cleaving truth from falsehood. The circle around the Khanda is the chakar. The chakar being a circle without a beginning or end symbolizes the perfection of God who is eternal. The chakar is surrounded by two curved swords called kirpans. These two swords symbolize the twin concepts of meeri and peeri – temporal and spiritual authority introduced by Guru Hargobind. They emphasize the equal emphasis that a Sikh must place on spiritual aspirations as well as obligations to society.” This information was obtained from http://www.sikhs.org/khanda.htm.

\n\nIS THERE A PARTICULAR ‘SIKH COLOR’? SAFFRON?
\n\nNo, there is no particular color for Sikhs or Sikhism. The Sikh flag, which is seen at almost every Gurdwara, is a bright orange/saffron color or dark blue. These represent traditional colors for Sikhs.

\n\nWHY DO SO MANY SIKHS HAVE A COMMON NAME, SINGH OR KAUR?
\n\nThe tenth Sikh Guru, Guru Gobind Singh, created the unique identity of the Sikhs and also gave all Sikh men one last name – Singh and all Sikh women another – Kaur. The reason for doing so is strongly rooted in the culture of South Asia. In that time period’s caste-ridden society and even today, someone’s last/family name signifies their social status and caste. Guru Gobind Singh wanted to remove these barriers between people, and create an egalitarian society. The word Singh means Lion and the word Kaur denotes Princess.

\n\nDO SOME SIKHS KEEP THEIR LAST (CASTE) NAME? WHY?
\n\nMany Sikh families have kept their family name, but have maintained Singh and Kaur as middle names.

\n\nDO SIKHS HAVE ANY DIETARY RESTRICTIONS? CAN SIKHS EAT MEAT?
\n\nSikh Gurus strongly forbade all rituals and superstitions. Sikhs are thus not allowed to eat any food prepared through a ritualistic process (e.g., Sikhs are not meant to eat Kosher or Halal). There is no mandate allowing or disallowing Sikhs to eat meat. Sikhs are also not supposed to drink alcohol or consume any other intoxicants.

\n\nIS THERE A SIKH CEREMONY OF INITIATION?
\n\nYes. Initiated Sikhs are said to have joined the “Khalsa.” Joining the Khalsa is an important step in one’s life. You are pledging your commitment to this faith and agreeing to live your life as a Sikh. This means that you must wear the five articles of faith, and carry Singh or Kaur as your last name.

\n\nHOW OLD DO YOU HAVE TO BE TO BE INITIATED?
\n\nThere is no prescribed age at which a Sikh should be initiated and can choose to do so whenever he or she is ready. According to the Rehat Maryada, only those who understand the significance of the ceremony and carry its discipline with sincerity should be initiated. It is important that once you are initiated you are committed to that lifestyle.

\n\nWHY DON’T SIKHS CUT OR SHAVE THEIR HAIR?
\n\nThe founders of the Sikh faith started the practice of keeping hair unshorn. Guru Gobind Singh, the tenth Sikh Guru, gave the Sikhs 5 articles of faith (including unshorn hair), which as a whole comprise the daily uniform of a Sikh. In other words, keeping your hair (kesh) and wearing a turban form an external identity for a Sikh.

\n\nHOW ABOUT PEOPLE WITH CUT HAIR WHO IDENTIFY THEMSELVES AS SIKH?
\n\nAll Sikhs are supposed to have uncut/untrimmed hair. But like in every religion, there are people who closely follow the religion and others who may not. Some people may cut their hair, but that does not exclude them from the Sikh community.

\n\nDO WOMEN SHAVE?
\n\nSikhs are not supposed to cut hair from any part of their body. All Sikhs are thus supposed to have unshorn hair, and Sikh women are to maintain a separate identity and not shave.

\n\nCAN I TOUCH SOMEONE’S TURBAN OR HAIR?
\n\nDo not touch someone’s turban or hair without asking, as it may make him/her uncomfortable.

\n\nWHAT IS UNDER YOUR TURBAN?
\n\nHair. Sikhs keep their hair unshorn and tie it in a bun or top knot on top of his/her head.

\n\nWHAT DOES THE COLOR OF THE TURBAN MEAN? DO ALL SIKHS WEAR THE SAME COLOR? WHY OR WHY NOT?
\n\nSikhs can wear any color or style of turban, and there are no significant colors. Some Sikhs wear very few colors and others have a broad color palette.

\n\nHOW CAN I TELL THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN SIKH TURBANS AND OTHER TURBANS?
\n\nEver Sikh ties his or her turban slightly differently. Remember that in America, 99% of the people you see wearing a turban will be Sikh. If you see someone wearing a turban and you are not sure if they are Sikh or not, ask them!
The Sikh turban is thus an article of faith. People of many other cultures and religions wear turbans, but none are required to do so by their religion.
Sikhs tie their turbans anew each day. Sikh turbans become a part of a Sikh’s body and are usually removed only in the privacy of the house.

\n\nDO WOMEN WEAR TURBANS?
\n\nJust like Sikh men, Sikh women are not supposed to cut their hair. In the Rehat Maryada, it is explicitly written that Sikh men wear a turban. There is nothing explicitly written about women, except that the turban is optional. Traditionally, women have always covered their head, but we’ve seen in the last 50 years, that women have deviated from this. There are many reasons for this change: globalization, cultural trends, and a lack of clarity in the Rehat Maryada. For Sikh women who tie a turban, the turban is just as much a part of their body and identity as it is for Sikh men!

\n\nWHY DO SIKHS WEAR A KIRPAN? WHAT SIZE KIRPAN DOES A SIKH CARRY?
\n\nA kirpan does not have a prescribed length. In most cases it is about 3-9 inches long. The kirpan serves as a reminder to fight against injustice and oppression. A Sikh understands that carrying a kirpan is a great responsibility. It is only intended to protect themselves or others.

\n\nDO KIDS IN SCHOOL CARRY A KIRPAN?
\n\nSome Sikhs that are younger have made the choice to become initiated, and as such, do wear a kirpan. Oftentimes, school personnel are aware that the Sikh student wears a kirpan, and both parties have come to an understanding as to how the student may wear his/her kirpan.

\n\nWHAT HAPPENS WHEN A SIKH GOES ON AN AIRPLANE? DO YOU HAVE TO TAKE THE KIRPAN OFF?
\n\nAt the present time, Sikhs put their kirpans into check-in luggage and do not carry it with them on an airplane.

\n\nCAN I VISIT A GURDWARA?
\nEveryone is welcome at a Gurdwara regardless of their race, religion, color or class. If you are interested in visiting a Gurdwara, feel free to reach out to Sikhs you know or contact community@sikhcoalition.org for additional suggestions and ideas.

\n\nDO YOU HAVE TO BE A SIKH TO READ THE GURU GRANTH SAHIB?
\n\nAnyone who wishes to can read the Guru Granth Sahib.

\n\nDO SIKHS HAVE A CLERGY? WHAT ABOUT GRANTHIS/GIANIS?
\n\nNo. Sikh gurus were very clear about each Sikh making her or his own journey and not depending on a clergy to show them the way. Sikhs do have Granthis/Gianis. These are people who have studied the Sikh scriptures extensively, and are available in the Gurdwaras as teachers. They often lead a congregation, but any members from the congregations – both men and women – can also perform the same ceremonies.

\n\nCAN WOMEN EXECUTE DUTIES IN A GURDWARA OR CONGREGATION?
\n\nYes. Sikhism does not delineate/define certain tasks to only men or only women. A woman can lead or take part in any service or ceremony just as a man would.

\n\nWHY ARE MEN AND WOMEN DIVIDED INTO SEPARATE SECTIONS WHILE SITTING IN THE GURDWARA?
\n\nSikh Gurus always taught equality between men and women. For instance, the Gurus decried the cultural climate that denied women access to religion and gave women equal rights as men in all spheres.
In Sikh congregations, men and women are asked to sit side by side – women on one side of the Guru Granth Sahib, and men on the other. There are both practical and cultural reasons for this practice. Since everyone sits on the floor, often unintentionally touching the person next to them when there is a large congregation, having such interaction with the member of the opposite gender is frequently inappropriate in the cultural context in which Sikhism arose.
However, in some smaller Gurdwaras, men and women may be seen sitting mixed in the congregation.

\n\nWHAT IS LANGAR?
\n\nThe Sikh Gurus instituted the unique practice of Langar. Langar is food that is cooked by the members of the community and served by members of the community, to all people at the Gurdwara. All Gurdwaras have a common kitchen, where Langar is cooked by volunteers and open to all. Langar is communal cooking, eating and sharing. Langar is eaten while sitting on the ground. The idea is to demonstrate equality of all people, irrespective of caste, creed, religion, race or sex. When Sikhism was sprouting in the South Asian subcontinent, the caste system stratified society. Higher castes would sit on stools and chairs and eat, while the lowest caste were not allowed to eat even in the same room, and usually on the floor, away from sight. The Gurus wanted Sikhs to always practice egalitarianism and communal responsibility. Langar represents one of the institutions the Gurus founded to break down caste barriers.

\n\nWHAT IS THE SIKH WEDDING CEREMONY?
\n\nThe Sikh marriage ceremony is called Anand Karaj. It is performed in the presence of the Guru Granth Sahib, the Sikh scripture. In a Sikh wedding, scripture is read from the Guru Granth Sahib, and after each section the couple walks around the Guru Granth Sahib, showing their commitment to the teachings being read. This is done four times. Following this, a communal prayer is said for the couple and religious hymns are sung. The ceremony may be performed by any initiated member of the Sikh faith. The prayers being read indicate that the couple pledge allegiance to each other as well as the Sikh way of life and make a commitment to working together to help each other realize the Divine Presence.

\n\nDO YOU BELIEVE IN AN AFTERLIFE? DO YOU BELIEVE IN HEAVEN/HELL, SALVATION?
\n\nSikh focus is on this lifetime. The Sikh Scripture ask Sikhs to make the best of their time on this earth, for this is one’s opportunity to accomplish her or his best and to make a connection with Waheguru – the One, Omnipotent Power. Sikhs are asked not to partake in rituals and superstitions and not to concentrate on what occurred before birth or after death. Sikh scripture repudiates a belief in a physical place called Heaven or Hell. Similarly, Sikhism rejects the notion of a Judgment Day. Sikhs believe in the doctrine of karma, which is a cosmic law that takes into account a person’s good and bad actions during his or her lifetime. The person then is rewarded or must endure suffering based on his deeds. The Sikh scripture supports the idea of reincarnation.

\n\nFUNERALS – WHERE, WHAT, HOW?
\n\nAccording to the Sikh Rehat, Sikhs may dispose the body of the dead in any way they like. Sikhs generally cremate their dead because it is clean, simple and environmentally friendly. The body is bathed and clothed in fresh clothes by family members, and community members say collective prayers. The ashes are usually gathered afterwards, and put afloat in a flowing body of water – returning the person’s last physical remains to nature.

\n\nWHAT DOES SIKHISM TEACH ABOUT OTHER RELIGIONS?
\n\nThe Sikh scripture, the Guru Granth Sahib, is the only major religious text which contains writings by teachers of other faiths. This is because Sikh gurus taught that there are many different ways of achieving a connection with the God. The Sikh way is one of these ways. If you are following the Sikh way, you must follow it to the best of your abilities, and with absolute devotion.

\n\nDOES SIKHISM TRY TO CONVERT OTHERS?
\n\nNo. Sikhism forbids proselytization or forced conversions. Sikhism believes that there are many paths to achieving attunement with the Divine. However, Sikhism welcomes those interested in learning about the religion. Thus, people might learn about Sikh faith and then even be initiated as Sikhs. There are Chinese Sikhs, African Sikhs etc. However, once someone is initiated as a Sikh, she or he must follow the Sikh path to the best of her or his ability.</string>
</resources>
